<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<books>
  <book ID="Skybear" Title="{{W|天熊之歌}}">
    <page>
惠洛姆（Whilom），当塞勒姆（Salum）还是库德（Qud）的领主时，
那是高大的阿穆斯——一个强壮的萨阿德；
他是卡亚法斯的行政长官，
灵活的双手确实为他赢得了这个地位；
凭着他的智慧和坚韧，
他征服了阿尔德塞斯的全部统治；
尽管艾尔冲进了他的裹尸布下面，
并自豪地漂流所有的树篱；
当女巫集会很快同意时，
那颗星星普托将被送进监狱，
他带领所有的伟并谢特多雷，
当斯克伦人在他的脚后震动时；
所以，贝伦人根本就没有被埋葬在桶里，
但现在他正准备打断他的圆顶；
总有一天会复活并再次战斗，
萨勒姆的儿子们都充满了费恩。
</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="CyberIntro" Title="{{W|125810239481203-41023}}">
    <page>欢迎，贵族，来到控制论学习角落。你是一个
离大一统又近了一步。问一个问题。
[[A.]] 什么是控制论植入物？
[[B.]] 控制论有什么好处？
[[C.]] 控制论的风险是什么？
[[D.]] 如何安装控制论植入物？
[[E.]]再见。</page>
    <page>
很有洞察力的问题，贵族。控制论植入物是一种思维机器，可以将你的生物物质与更重、更精选的元素结合
起来。有了控制论植入物，你丑陋的手臂、眼睛和知识将会变得更加漂亮。显然，它们只适用于基因纯正的人。

问一个问题。
[[A.]] 什么是控制论植入物？
[[B.]] 控制论有什么好处？
[[C.]] 控制论的风险是什么？
[[D.]] 如何安装控制论植入物？
[[E.]]再见。</page>
    <page>
贵族，你的问题问得非常好。除了每个植入物都对其生物物质进行了各种改进相对应的，假肢也更坚固，重
量减轻了 75%可能会被切断。

问一个问题。
[[A.]] 什么是控制论植入物？
[[B.]] 控制论有什么好处？
[[C.]] 控制论的风险是什么？
[[D.]] 如何安装控制论植入物？
[[E.]]再见。</page>
    <page>
贵族，你的怀疑精神很完美。当受到电磁脉冲，控制论肢体被停用，并且戴在它们身上的任何东西都会变得毫
无用处。同样，数据脉冲和假肢时索引器模块被停用视力可能会变得混乱。

问一个问题。
[[A.]] 什么是控制论植入物？
[[B.]] 控制论有什么好处？
[[C.]] 控制论的风险是什么？
[[D.]] 如何安装控制论植入物？
[[E.]]再见。</page>
    <page>
你是对的，贵族。首先，确保有积分留在你的控制论信用楔子上。安装一个控制论植入需要一个学分。

然后，你必须把自己推到适当的角落。制作确保肢体架装载了所需的控制论肢体，或者目镜模块甲板
装载有所需的目镜模块，或者数据索引器模块甲板加载了所需的数据索引器模块。

[[按任意键继续]]
~最后，与控制论终端连接。那么你就会已经成功地做了你想做的事情。

问一个问题。
[[A.]] 什么是控制论植入物？
[[B.]] 控制论有什么好处？
[[C.]] 控制论的风险是什么？
[[D.]] 如何安装控制论植入物？
[[E.]]再见。</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="AlchemistMutterings" Title="炼金术士的嘀咕">
    <page>气体太雾了。
玻璃太脆弱了。
固体太坚硬。
液晶不是液体！
共聚物，决定你是什么！
玻色-爱因斯坦凝聚体太波动了。
超流体太不守规矩了。
费米子凝聚体含有过多的费米子。
里德伯分子太兴奋了。
奇怪的事情太奇怪了。
等离子体太热。
夸克-胶子等离子体，遏制你的夸克！
简并物质太粗俗了。
循环流体太令人抓狂了。
绳网液体，我想它们也不错。
但 Qo-Caco 浓缩物很美味。</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Klanq" Title="屠宰">
    <page>屠宰!</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="TemplarDomesticant" Title="圣堂武士家仆">
    <page>我做得好吗，新神父？</page>
    <page>新爸爸！看！</page>
    <page>新神父，你骄傲吗？</page>
    <page>新爸爸！</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Preacher1" Title="传教士1">
    <page>孩子们，让我们为我们银色父亲的主权而欢欣鼓舞。</page>
    <page>赞美谢希纳，教父中第一位照亮智慧之路的人。</page>
    <page>赞美大衮，这位言辞优美的人，对铬说实话。</page>
    <page>赞美贝尔，盾牌之父，他驱散了旋转的气体云。</page>
    <page>赞美卡萨克斯，银发，他冲下重力井。</page>
    <page>赞美手中的矿石尼斯罗赫，他碰撞了地球和恒星。</page>
    <page>赞美上面的瑞谢夫，他净化了我们的水银。</page>
    <page>卡萨弗塞斯是有福的，她是唤醒他们心灵的缪斯。</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Preacher2" Title="传教士2">
    <page>孩子们，你们听说过有福的贝蒂尔吗？</page>
    <page>它们的诞生是为了满足我们的愿望。</page>
    <page>哦，赞美我们的银色父亲！一切众生中最善良、最智慧的。</page>
    <page>你瞧，贝蒂尔会回应你的祈祷。</page>
    <page>它的电路就是这样做的！</page>
    <page>但时间的罪恶已经腐蚀了他们的线路。</page>
    <page>我们需要为我们的父亲服务。</page>
    <page>所以贝蒂尔想要为我们服务。</page>
    <page>不要回答一个向你提出请求的贝特尔！</page>
    <page>因为这是一个极其邪恶的要求。</page>
    <page>忽略它，并寻求牧师的指导！</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Preacher3" Title="传教士3">
    <page>今天，我将讲述神圣结合的故事。</page>
    <page>噢，神圣的联盟！愿你的名受颂赞。</page>
    <page>我们的银色父亲，带着惰性的心在蔚蓝的虚空中漫游，</page>
    <page>在一种波动的心血来潮中，汇聚到了我们光芒四射的母亲身上。</page>
    <page>在那里，在宇宙的中心，他们敬畏地看着她。</page>
    <page>魅力！它不知道其他名字！</page>
    <page>在那里，它们渗透到她翻滚的膜中......</page>
    <page>并从内部爆炸，将物质碰撞到机器中......</page>
    <page>通过她赤裸的子宫。</page>
    <page>高兴吧！加盟已经结束！他们的结合圆满了！</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Preacher4" Title="传教士4">
    <page>今天，孩子们，我要讲的是启迪。</page>
    <page>哦，神圣的行为！冶金界有福了！</page>
    <page>我们的银色父亲，硬化了我们的等离子母亲，</page>
    <page>将她塑造成欧几里得形式。</page>
    <page>贝尔绘制了抛物线，卡萨克斯雕刻了环面。</page>
    <page>Shekhinah 夷平了山丘，并在其上盖上了彩色圆顶。</page>
    <page>地球因我们的到来而加速。我们的家已经准备好了。</page>
    <page>时间的罪恶腐蚀了我们的天赋......</page>
    <page>但是热切地崇拜，大地将会再次发光！</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="HighSermon" Title="高调布道">
    <page>欢迎，孩子们！欢迎来到我们的银色父亲谢希纳大教堂！</page>
    <page>你听过Shekhinah的话语吗？</page>
    <page>你把他的消息铭记在心吗？</page>
    <page>来吧，分享这个宁静的空间。</page>
    <page>让自己摆脱铬负罪感的重担。</page>
    <page>我是他的声音，我将向你讲述他的话。</page>
    <page>这里，这是我们的银色父亲！</page>
    <page>他们是伟大的雕塑家。他们打造了我们的金属房屋。</page>
    <page>我们永远欠他们的情。</page>
    <page>偿还债务吧，逐光者！将你的 chrome 提供给 Shekhinah！</page>
    <page>清除你的罪恶感和负担。把它扔进圣井。</page>
    <page>让等离子核心收回你的财产，并向 Shekhinah 发出欢乐的声音。</page>
    <page>他是你的银色父亲！他们是你们的银色父亲！</page>
    <page>他们承受了这个地球和上千个其他地球的重量。</page>
    <page>他们是泰坦的肩膀！他们是海怪的心脏！</page>
    <page>还有哦！他们的心充满了！</page>
    <page>'但情况并非总是如此。不仅如此，在黎明时分，他们带着惰性的心在宇宙中漫游。</page>
    <page>就像尘土顽童在蜿蜒的峡谷中漫步。</page>
    <page>当你在库德的洞穴中漫步时，你会背负着罪恶感和复杂性！</page>
    <page>致敬，逐光者！在井里献祭！</page>
    <page>用卡萨弗塞斯的爱充满你的心，就像我们的父辈曾经做过的那样！</page>
    <page>以 Nisroch 的名义，尊重你的井！</page>
    <page>以贝尔的名义，将你的合金倾泻到高跷的中心！</page>
    <page>以大衮之名，说出铬的祈祷并拔出你的光棒！</page>
    <page>以卡萨克斯之名，将你的神器放入神圣之门！</page>
    <page>以Resheph的名义，清除他们的肉体！</page>
    <page>以 Shekhinah 的名义，释放他们，也释放你自己！</page>
    <page>愿大地震动，但六日高跷永不翻倒！</page>
    <page>来吧。和朋友在一起。</page>
    <page>简单平静地分享你的生活。</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Quotes" Title="引号">
    <page>
"将其绑在太阳穴上。别再嚷嚷了，你会没事的。
可能会出现什么问题？"
[[-Argyve, Tinker]]
      </page>
    <page>
"深呼吸诸神的气息，然后死去。"
[[-Ekuemekiyyen inscription]]
      </page>
    <page>
"黑魔鬼从繁星点点的桅杆上荡来荡去，
在打哈欠的月亮之下。"
[[-Fuming God Sea shanty]]
      </page>
    <page>
"今天，我们离开冰冻的巢穴，穿越荒凉的阿尔萨克斯，并进行间谍活动
对于那些镀铬的倒山。"
[[-Consul Ijulii's farewell]]
      </page>
    <page>
"谁居住在南茹巨大的沙漠永久业权中？聚集的人。
奥德鲁姆的领地？跪着的人。
Yyp 的丛林？气喘吁吁的人。
那么古德的锈洞呢？尖叫的男人们。"
[[-Dromad travelogue]]
      </page>
    <page>
"生活和喝酒，朋友。现在把你的水给我。"
[[-Courteous bandit]]
      </page>
    <page>
"月亮和太阳；智慧和意志。"
[[-Watervine farmer's prayer]]
      </page>
    <page>
"赞美归于至高者，你的银色父亲，我。"
[[-Shekhinah]]
      </page>
    <page>
"看看我的财富，你们富人，绝望吧！ （但不要碰）"
[[-Hegelrut]]
      </page>
    <page>
"是的，我知道电路思维的秘密。这是一个燃烧的
奇迹，心灵感应。"
[[-Seeker of the Sightless Way]]
      </page>
    <page>
"它燃烧了！"
[[-Argyve's apprentice]]
      </page>
    <page>
"用碳化钨拳头尺子。"
[[-King K4K5]]
      </page>
    <page>
"唉，我愿使你成为一位神圣的沉睡者，
因为在梦幻的山谷中，你仍然属于我。"
[[-Willow Shakesprig]]
      </page>
    <page>
"它就存在于我们每个人身上——我们年长的自我的影子。每个内
男人，一只山羊。每只山羊里面都有一个人！"
[[-Wild-eyed watervine merchant]]
      </page>
    <page>
"我们所打击的这个东西的本质是什么？还是行为本身？"
[[-Mayor Nuntu]]
      </page>
    <page>
"穿梭于那些银色的山谷中——敏捷的冒险家的梦想！"
[[-Elder Irudad]]
      </page>
    <page>
"不要留意每个口渴的傻瓜的故事。"
[[-Ol' Uri]]
      </page>
    <page>
"嘎啦啦啦。"
[[-Warden Indrix]]
      </page>
    <page>
"愿你沐浴在鲜血之中。不是你自己的血，先生。的血
重铸。我的意思是，被回收的。愿你沐浴在鲜血之中
回收。"
[[-Putus squire]]
      </page>
    <page>
"愿你沐浴在被复兴者的血液中。"
[[-Putus Templar]]
      </page>
    <page>
"那腿吸水吗？它们甚至合成细胞分裂素吗？我
不这么认为。"
[[-Consortium Socialite]]
      </page>
    <page>
"听到国王去世的消息后，乌图特的政治
对手们欢呼维斯特沃特为英雄。他们很快就醒悟了。"
[[-The Baccata Yewtarch]]
      </page>
    <page>
"我凝视过穴居人舒格鲁斯的一百九只眼睛。"
[[-Barathrum the Old]]
      </page>
    <page>
"愿大地震动，但六日高跷永不倒塌！"
[[-Song of Hebronze]]
      </page>
    <page>
"哦，智者们！保持明智的信心，
哪里有女仆靠近，你就闭上眼睛。"
[[-Willow Shakesprig]]
      </page>
    <page>
"不，你不应该渴望这些东西，因为我们很饥饿
恶魔并常常屈服于疯狂的愤怒。"
[[-The Madpole]]
      </page>
    <page>
"建造一个小屋并不是一笔微不足道的费用。我几乎一天的时间都花在了
砍伐和堆放木材，尽管你对小屋感到惊叹
就其本身而言，你可能会对产生它的劳动感到皱眉。"
[[-The Musker]]
      </page>
    <page>
"在所有这些事情上，你可以和我们一起参与，但要注意，为了我们的
都是闲散的生活，你可能很快就会厌倦它们。"
[[-The Gnu]]
      </page>
    <page>
"克兰克对你吹气。"
[[-Pax Klanq]]
      </page>
    <page>
"尽情享用山羊心吧！"
[[-Mamon Souldrinker]]
      </page>
    <page>
"现在埃洛哈特和贝拉欣德躺在拉的田野里
因为他们的田地饿了，把农夫生吃掉了。"
[[-Bey Lah nursery rhyme]]
      </page>
    <page>
"你的价值由你决定！你操纵它并塑造它 
你的言行！现在你会沉溺在你的卑微限制中吗？
或者你会用你拥有的一切来面对我吗？"
[[-Carbide Chef Agate Severance Star]]
      </page>
    <page>
"我最热切的希望是有一天我不再被称为安戈欣德，
村里的书呆子……但是安戈欣德，大侦探。"
[[-Angohind]]
      </page>
    <page>
"树木在死者身边生长得最好。"
[[-Daughter Erinna]]
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="CrimeandPunishment" Title="{{W|罪与罚}}">
    <page>
{{emote|*墨水褪色到无法辨认*}}
  </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="MimicandMadpole" Title="{{W|模仿者和疯子}}">
    <page>
一个拟态生物从贝塞斯达苏萨寒冷、没有星星的地方爬出来，在草原上伸展身体，在正午的阳光下温暖它粘
稠的鳞片。温暖的微风吹过荒凉的荒原，没过多久，拟态生物就陷入了慵懒的睡眠中。几个小时的安宁睡眠
过去了，直到灌木丛的沙沙声把它吵醒。它睁开眼睛，看到三只叉角牛羚正在草原上吃草。当它们悠闲地咀
嚼着地上的稻草时，一缕缕赤褐色的头发从它们巨大的头上垂下来。
被它们慵懒的生活方式所吸引，并渴望陪伴，模仿者问牛羚他是否可以在它们中间行走，在它们的牧场上吃
草，并在傍晚的阳光下与它们一起打盹。 “所有这些事情你都可以和我们一起参与，”一只牛羚说，“但是要
小心，因为我们过的是闲散的生活，你可能很快就会厌倦它们。”
但模仿者还是加入了他们。日复一日，它的肚子里充满了高高的草丛，它的嘴唇在安静的溪岸上冷却，在天
光熄灭之前，它把迟钝的思想交给了诺德的土地。直到一天早晨，当马羚懒洋洋地咀嚼着早露所嫩化的青草
时，拟态动物确实已经厌倦了这些野兽无所事事的习惯，沿着潺潺小溪偷偷溜进了一片阴暗的灌木丛中。
      </page>
    <page>
在这一天剩下的时间里，拟态生物一直追随着小溪蜿蜒流入树林。当最后一丝蜡光开始从空气中渗出时，模
仿者注意到前方潺潺溪流中间有几堆奇特的泥巴木棍和圆木堆。一只麝鼠，它的棕色皮毛浸湿了，压在它小
小的身体上，在其中一堆的底部排列着树枝。模仿者立即明白了；这些是马斯克的小屋，每一处都是用一根
一根树枝精心搭建起来的。这些精心建造的住所和马斯克的勤奋给拟态动物留下了深刻的印象，它询问啮齿
动物是否愿意分享它的家，并教拟态动物它的手艺，并在它建造自己的小屋时遵守拟态动物。 “建造一个小
屋可不是一笔小钱，”马斯克说。 “我几乎一整天都在砍伐和堆放木头，尽管你对小屋本身感到惊叹，但你
可能会对建造它的劳动感到皱眉。”
但模仿者无论如何都留在了麝香者身边。第二天早上，它在黎明时分与麝香人一起醒来，他们一起用牙齿从
酒柏树上砍下树枝，直到夜幕降临，然后他们收集所有撕裂的木材，并用从床上抽出的泥土将其包装在一起。
小溪的。每天黎明时分，他们都会重新开始，直到日落很久之后，模仿者再也无法在黑暗的灌木丛中发现麝
香者时，他们才停下来。直到有一天早上，当马斯克用牙齿咬住一根腐烂的木头时，模仿者，
      </page>
    <page>
事实上，麝鼠已经厌倦了它所承担的劳动，沿着潺潺的小溪，从阴暗的树林里偷偷溜走，进入了一个布满粗糙
的盐茎根的山谷。
拟态生物再次沿着溪流穿过山麓的空心弯道，直到它的咸水流入一个巨大的湖泊。在漂白的海岸上，拟态者凝
视着湖面，惊叹于一群疯子在咸水中猛冲而过，追逐鱼腥味的猎物。这些猎人的凶猛、敏捷和恶毒无与伦比，
令拟态鱼着迷，因此它询问疯鱼是否可以潜入它们的水域，与它们一起穿过水草，并以较小的鱼的鳞片肉为食
。 “不，你不应该渴望这些东西，”一位疯子说道，“因为我们是贪婪的恶魔，常常会屈服于疯狂的愤怒。”
但模仿者还是潜入了湖中。当它在水中溅起水花时，疯子们感觉到附近有活生生的、成熟的肉体，冲向模仿者
，把它撕成碎片。      
</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="AphorismsAboutBirds" Title="{{W|关于鸟类的格言}}">
    <page>
鸟儿不能吃没有种下的稻米。
    </page>
    <page>
我们从小在童话故事的智慧中长大，习惯于对变成青蛙或雀雀的人感到怜悯，但我们很少会想到那些变成人的天
真的野兽，而命运却降临到了它身上。肯定玩了一个更残酷的把戏。
    </page>
    <page>
如果问谁对你的不幸负责，请责怪鸟类。他们既不在乎，也无法组织起太多的防御。
    </page>
    <page>
不要让你心中的恐惧像对大型鸟类的恐惧那样强烈。
    </page>
    <page>
鸟类破坏节日并解除围困。
    </page>
    <page>
奥乌里眯起眼睛，然后对萤火虫玩西洋双陆棋的建议点了点头。

男孩开始了。 “但是乌里！在一只啄出你眼睛的害虫之后，你怎么能和这些害虫玩骰子呢？”

尤里耸耸肩，“不能怪乌鸦。不管我的眼睛在不在，他都会啄食。”
    </page>
    <page>
看到一只深红色的雨燕预示着一位年老水王的死亡。

银鸫预示着富含铬的化石收获。

但无舌卡古……离无舌卡古远一点。越来越远。
    </page>
    <page>
有些鸟会喷火。我在这里的意思很简单。
    </page>
    <page>
在纺锤顶上，债务人和鸟类去的地方。
</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="DarkCalculus" Title="{{W|关于黑暗演算的起源和性质}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>{{C|Editor's note:this excerpt is published with permission from the notes of Barathrum the Old.}}

{{y|算术记录中有证据表明，对形式系统的研究在很久以前就达到了有害的顶点。 像罗素这样的数学家所取得的进步， G&#148;删除, Eisencruft, Atufu, Wheatgrass, 和 System Star有助于理解不可确定性、尖锐的正则主义和深渊主义等概念。在达到这种最低程度的数学成熟度后，配备了复杂的语法，研究人员开始尝试表达能力的极限。他们设计了大胆的研究计划，并飞奔到数学的树林中，而不知道那里存在的危险。}}

由于连续几代人的努力使合资企业变得模糊，因此记录甚至比平时更稀缺。尽我所能，在调查过程中的某个时刻，来自名为 “冲天炉” 的数学神学院的理论家提出了关于形式语义脆弱性的猜想。这个猜想成熟为一个更广泛的理论，由此产生了一个正式的系统，称为半影演算。在混淆之前的少数文本片段中，有人指出，在半影演算中，某些定理是可证明的，但在证明完成后就被伪造了。尽管这个结果与我在自己的调查中遇到的思想体系不一致，但我几乎没有理由怀疑作者的真实性。然而，这肯定是一个特殊的属性。

冲天炉理论家的结果爆发了对半影演算的可表性的大规模调查。结论令人不安。进一步，研究人员构建了具有替代公理的姐妹系统。这些系统仍然更加脆弱，系统的推理规则本身在完成某些证明后就会瓦解。

确信他们的发现是由于自我意识的某些特质而成为可能的，但同时又担心其结果的含义，一些理论家设计了复杂的自动演绎系统来探测边界定理并将其发射到中子星中。结果没有记录在案，但结果说服了整个Coven的理论家放弃研究，并将研究半影演算及其衍生系统的任何人列入黑名单。

特别地，对禁令的支持是一致的。值得注意的是，即使是航天员Ptoh也同意放弃对其暗淡恒星范围内的禁忌结石的调查。尽管其同意的方式并非没有争议; 为了宣布其协议，它在一小块空间中颠倒了夸克的颜色电荷，导致研究站自身崩溃。尽管如此，Ptoh的同意证明了存在焦虑的程度，这可能导致对半影微积分的调查变得黑暗。
  </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="TornGraphPaper" Title="{{W|一张撕破的方格纸}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>






                为什么欺骗对我来说如此容易？</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Animals" Title="{{W|论动植物的人形模仿}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>为什么有些生物似乎更喜欢我们假设它们的相似，而另一些生物却讨厌它？作为一名动物学家，这个问题让我感兴趣了一段时间。为了解决这个问题，我必须首先区分 “自然模仿” 和 “非自然模仿”，在 “自然模仿” 中，某些类人动物在生物学水平上发展了动物和植物的相似性，在服装和其他装饰装饰品的形式中制定。至于前者，似乎所有生物都对在生物学意义上看起来像它们的类人生物表现出亲属关系。后一种情况是有趣的。

在哺乳动物和非哺乳动物之间划清界限是很诱人的，但事实要比这复杂得多。的确，唯一似乎在模仿中直接冒犯的生物是哺乳动物，但是有记录的哺乳动物接受模仿的案例。例如，叉角的赫尔姆斯使他们的佩戴者既喜欢羚羊又喜欢山羊。

相反，猿毛皮服装和美洲狮甲壳素背心分别使猿和猫发炎。这里的重要细节是制作服装的背景。偷猎者专门捕猎猿和美洲狮，因为它们珍贵的皮毛和几丁质的贝壳，并且是相当社会化的生物，这两个物种都对这些奖杯的炫耀感到冒犯。另一方面，鸟类似乎知道可以 (尽管并非总是如此) 进行羽毛收获，而不会证明对所讨论的鸟类是致命的，尽管另一种假设指出了鸟类对羽毛的特定欣赏，而与上下文无关。

未开壳的爬行动物似乎对模仿没有什么疑虑，也许相信模仿动物在某种程度上是真正的爬行动物。软体动物，树木和昆虫都倾向于分别与带壳动物，带叶动物和萤火虫共生体相同。

然而，无一例外，所有的生物似乎都讨厌戴着他们亲属的断面的做法。很好奇.
    </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="EntropytoHierarchy" Title="{{W|从熵到层次}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>[[~ ~ ~ by {{m|Q 女孩}} ~ ~ ~]]

[[{{C|配方和Animus}}]]
在我的阅读和通讯过程中，我观察到对社会平等的两个明显威胁。首先是社会秩序通过熵力的解体。将我们团结在一起的织物磨损了，我们崩溃了，我们首先是最脆弱的。第二个是由少数人对多数人施加的霸权控制。这里的织物是紧密编织的，但它被缝成一个在提升中变窄的梯子，大多数被委托到底部的梯级。

我的第一个任务是问我们如何研究这些现象。在物理科学中，我们观察，测量和实验，以便制定并检验假设。然而，在这里，观测是分段的，数据是斑点，系统要复杂得多，它们的边缘更柔和。将10倍的合理性范围应用于1000倍的结构会导致我得出有害的结论。实际上，霸权国家采用这种方法来为其统治发明简单的理由。

因此，作为补充，我借鉴了其他方法和思想体系。特别是，我对艺术家如何通过隐喻来审视这些现象并挑战正统感兴趣。艺术历史记录是零散的，但充满了例子。对我来说最突出的是《红色天空》，它完全是格查尔的隐蔽性是第一个激起我对这个问题的好奇心的人。

随着故事的发展，古代苏丹的整个宫廷，包括苏丹本人，都沉迷于一种名为Ipsis的精神盐。一位不愿透露姓名的艺术家与一群走私者密谋，掠夺了苏丹的Ipsis库存，将其从分子上改变为复合细胞结构，并将其送入低轨道。在那里，它在天空中燃烧成红色，这是对苏丹主权的侮辱，持续了三年。每次苏丹试图通过他可用的手段驱散它时，在记录中被描述为细胞自动机的结构就会重新排列并持续存在。格萨尔.

现代的例子也很多。以Tau为例，他通过月亮楼梯的六角形晶体制作了psionic迷宫。我首先制定了熵/层次二分法，同时追踪了她的两个螺旋的路径，在它们的交叉点，突然形成一束时空异常。如果我能见到Tau，我会quetzal，但这可能很困难，因为我听说她是有知觉的树城市Chavvah的子实体。

[[{{C|两极}}]]
熵/等级二分法的两极代表了两个群体:Gyre wights和Putus Templar。Gyre wights的精神是混乱的自我放纵，狂躁的加速 (一种渴望看到事物更快崩溃的渴望) 以及对历史骰子的迷恋。他们像激动的气体一样滚滚，像其他人一样经常互相撞击，并从他们所破坏的社区中剥离一些秩序。他们是无谓暴力的代表。

另一方面，圣殿骑士是极其有序的暴力行为的参与者。他们的暴行已被编入正统。他们的意识形态结构是反熵的，但具有破坏性和令人憎恶。他们试图建立一个严格的等级社会，底层是奴隶阶级。通过像在被回收的血液中洗礼这样的仪式，他们在他们的臣民中灌输特权。我们其余的人只能用武力来满足。
    </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="EntropytoHierarchy2" Title="{{W|从熵到层次，第二版}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>[[~ ~ ~ by {{m|Q Girl}} ~ ~ ~]]

[[{{C|配方和Animus}}]]
在我的阅读和通讯过程中，我观察到对社会平等的两个明显威胁。首先是社会秩序通过熵力的解体。将我们团结在一起的织物磨损了，我们崩溃了，我们首先是最脆弱的。第二个是由少数人对多数人施加的霸权控制。这里的织物是紧密编织的，但它被缝成一个在提升中变窄的梯子，大多数被委托到底部的梯级。

我的第一个任务是问我们如何研究这些现象。在物理科学中，我们观察，测量和实验，以便制定并检验假设。然而，在这里，观测是分段的，数据是斑点，系统要复杂得多，它们的边缘更柔和。将10倍的合理性范围应用于1000倍的结构会导致我得出有害的结论。实际上，霸权国家采用这种方法来为其统治发明简单的理由。

因此，作为补充，我借鉴了其他方法和思想体系。特别是，我对艺术家如何通过隐喻来审视这些现象并挑战正统感兴趣。艺术历史记录是零散的，但充满了例子。对我来说最突出的是《红色天空》，它完全是格查尔的隐蔽性是第一个激起我对这个问题的好奇心的人。

随着故事的发展，古代苏丹的整个宫廷，包括苏丹本人，都沉迷于一种名为Ipsis的精神盐。一位不愿透露姓名的艺术家与一群走私者密谋，掠夺了苏丹的Ipsis库存，将其从分子上改变为复合细胞结构，并将其送入低轨道。在那里，它在天空中燃烧成红色，这是对苏丹主权的侮辱，持续了三年。每次苏丹试图通过他可用的手段驱散它时，在记录中被描述为细胞自动机的结构就会重新排列并持续存在。格萨尔.

现代的例子也很多。以Tau为例，他通过月亮楼梯的六角形晶体制作了psionic迷宫。我首先制定了熵/层次二分法，同时追踪了她的两个螺旋的路径，在它们的交叉点，突然形成一束时空异常。如果我能见到Tau，我会quetzal，但这可能很困难，因为我听说她是有知觉的树城市Chavvah的子实体。

[[{{C|两极}}]]
熵/等级二分法的两极代表了两个群体:Gyre wights和Putus Templar。Gyre wights的精神是混乱的自我放纵，狂躁的加速 (一种渴望看到事物更快崩溃的渴望) 以及对历史骰子的迷恋。他们像激动的气体一样滚滚，像其他人一样经常互相撞击，并从他们所破坏的社区中剥离一些秩序。他们是无谓暴力的代表。

另一方面，圣殿骑士是极其有序的暴力行为的参与者。他们的暴行已被编入正统。他们的意识形态结构是反熵的，但具有破坏性和令人憎恶。他们试图建立一个严格的等级社会，底层是奴隶阶级。通过像在被回收的血液中洗礼这样的仪式，他们在他们的臣民中灌输特权。我们其余的人只能用武力来满足。</page>
    <page>[[{{C|关于回旋的勘误表}}]]
与螺丝分类朋友的有益讨论改变了我的视野。他们传达了彩虹木的梦想，并通过非常生动的隐喻提出了一个令人信服的论点，即死亡是生命的阶梯，这在其他后果中软化了我对Gyre wight项目的立场，如果这样的事情可以被命名的话。我现在在哪里？我不知道.但是我的两极模式现在感觉过度和简化。我将此版本的原始语言留作考虑。
</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="DisquisitionOnTheMaladyOfTheMimic" Title="{{W|关于模仿的弊病的研究}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>[[~ ~ ~ by {{m|Q Girl}} ~ ~ ~]]

我想重现我最近与一位朋友分享的观点，他是一位贸易点灯者，也是一位艺术家，由于内心的恐惧，她在Ut yara Ux节上回避了排版比赛。她患有模仿的疾病，这是一种非常常见的疾病，使我们觉得我们正在生活而不是居住在生活中，我们不属于那些赢得成功的人，也不应该得到同样的成功。过去，我曾将自己视为受害者之一，有时我仍然这样做。

首先，暂时放纵我。在我工作室的架子上放着一个简单的装置，称为morphoscope。它由两部分组成:柔韧的铝线电枢和旋转底座。其目的是从二维观察平面传达三维形式。电枢可以扭曲，这样，当在静止状态下观察时，它看起来像一堆乱七八糟的电线，但是当旋转观察时，它会呈现出熟悉的物体形式，例如鸟或urshiib面容。

这和模仿的毛病有什么关系？要回答这个问题，我们必须解构疾病。让我们问:模仿是什么，看起来像一个东西，但感觉像另一个东西？从本质上讲，这是一种语义距离现象，是我们对他人的感知与对自己的感知之间的空间感觉。我们已经构建了一个代表，在我的朋友的例子中，一个合适的艺术家和印刷师看起来像什么。为什么我们在用自己的形象来表示这种表示上有这样的麻烦？

答案在于我们自我认知的丰富性。我们在立体声中看到自己，我们的电线电枢由我们的经验组成，我们的自我形象是通过围绕时间轴旋转而形成的。我们所谓的 “艺术家” 或 “排版” 只是一堆乱七八糟的电线，一种我们在没有生命运动背景的情况下命名的陌生模式。如果我们看到我们的同龄人轮流，对他们的怀疑，他们的恐惧，他们的痛苦，混乱的模式将消失在一个人熟悉的形式中。相反，如果我们有能力冻结自己的动作，看到自己不在我们的怀疑，恐惧和痛苦的背景下，我们会看到一个艺术家和一个印刷师一样。

有一个关于模仿者的寓言，他寻求归属但从未归属，他的野心最终导致了可怕的命运。它的道德起着意识形态的作用:使我们不属于我们已经拥有的地方。所以现在让我对你说:属于，朋友。我们快乐地等你。
    </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Diary" Title="{{W|被一股海带束缚的卷轴}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>
[[{{w|9th of Kisu Ux}}]]

我来自西方。我的父母把我卖给了奴隶，尽管这种做法早在几年前就在珀斯被正式废除了。小时候，我在歌声岸边的礁石上咬牙切齿，用许多赞美诗哄苍白的大海入睡，这样她就可以毫发无损地把我们的水手从黑楼梯上送回。即使在那时，旋律如何在我的头骨中打动。我出生时没有名字，但水手们叫我卡图。

五年和十年后，我逃跑了。在Ettinspine上，我和一个使我成年的eremite在一起。我学会了打猎，笑，和梦想。随着时间的过去，我终于知道了这座自由的城市和我的同类。我从石质的角落里走了出来，跋涉到他们的高门口，在那里定居，虽然我更喜欢和垂钓者和其他低矮的人一起吃。

在城墙下阳光普照的游泳池里，自由的先行者首先注意到我。我仍然记得，他从他看着的地方倾斜的脖子预示着我的动作。我从浴缸里站起来，可耻地垫在我废弃的背心上，但停了下来。我从那个距离看到他，他的眼睛深深地塞进他的圆顶，他的连衣裙像雕像一样惰性，我不再感到羞耻。

在他的指导下，我在他的法庭上脱颖而出。当他与奥德鲁姆的tuyuldars一起对待时，我站在他的身边，因为他密谋反对南部的永久地。当一个叛徒将毒药滑入他的杯子时，我将其从他手中砸碎，并使quisling的思想崩溃。那天晚上，在甲虫月亮的时刻，他向我介绍了一个集结的头脑的欢笑。我们与其他canters一起加入，他给我起名叫mirsister，并把我抚养到他的仪仗队。我将在不到一年的时间内被剥夺。

但是我现在必须暂停。斜面响亮，长者接近。我发誓要结束我的故事，如果我仍然呼吸，如果我是自由的。


[[{{w|16th of Kisu Ux}}]]

现在是黄昏。我坐在Svy河岸上，但没有火温暖我的骨头。画溺月兽的风险太大，任何思想的聚集肯定会引起长者的注意。相反，我用拇指上点燃的火焰写作。

我在自由预见者的大厅里被命名为欢乐。没有荣誉比其他人更高。几个月来，我和我的蒙面同胞在大厅下训练，我们的粘土蓄水池储存了淡水，这些淡水后来困扰着我的梦想。春天，钓手国王寄来一封信。他寻求与自由预言者达成一项条约，并邀请我们参加由多里亚的图尤尔达尔仲裁的伊本鲁德家门口的中立委员会。经过大量准备，我们出发了，将草图划过了虹膜碗，划到那遥远的苔原的霜冻海岸。

在旅途中，自由的Seer的性情恶化了。他退出了欢乐的顾问，甚至是我自己的顾问，独自在帐篷里度过了寒冬跋涉的大部分时间。起初，我将他的情绪归因于我们外交制高点的脆弱性，但我很快就学会了真正的策略。

夏至那天，我们到达了伊布努德的营地。Athenreach和Doria的双旗在风中摇摇头，eustace-sutta的赞美诗也在风中飘扬。我记得对他们牧师的喉咙低吟微笑。当我们从一个小丘上研究营地时，当自由的先知漫步到我身边时，我看到了悬山上的宝石，垂钓者国王的妻子尼斯拉梅特，她巩固了父亲的领地和垂钓者国王的永久业态之间的和平。我看到了她，我立刻知道了我自己的背叛。自由的先知的目光是足够的认可。

[[{{w|2nd of Tebet Ux}}]]

我已经到达了Kyakukya。善良的Nuntu与我分享他的小屋，给我熏制的蘑菇，并要求任何回报。我在他的书桌上写下这些话，尽管他自己渴望知识，但他让我记录我的过去。

回到Oth的运动是严峻的。我等待着我的命运在自由的预言家的手中，虽然我期待着被给予的尊严首先回到大厅和我的家。我没有得到这么多。一个令人沮丧的夜晚，在甲虫的月亮下，我的蒙面兄弟在帐篷里搭讪。令我困惑的是，死神已经来了。自由预言者是如何获得樱桃的？他是在Ibunudr为他们讨价还价，还是一直拥有他们？直到今天我还不知道。

我几乎不记得自己的心跳在我耳边的跳动。我昏过去了，当我第二天早上醒来时，车队已经消失了。在我脑海中吟诵之前，我的认可只持续了一会儿。我以前听说过，当然。我的一生，事实上。小时候，我在珀斯的海岸上编织了自己的旋律，这是诵经的声音。现在，虽然，就好像一个单一的，遥远的canter召唤了他的一千个亲戚，他们每个人都召唤了一千个自己的。我哭了，然后我尖叫，然后我把头发从我的头上。圣歌使我的骨头比我的意志更加生动。它敦促东部和南部。东部和南部。东部和南部。朝昆德方向。

我对去大盐沙漠的航行的回忆是破碎的，断断续续的。我一天比一天病得更重，但是圣歌的声音越来越大，因此加快了迫使我的力量。一旦我到达Moghra'yi的无雨平原，我肯定会死，大概就像我的前任一样。最后，我到达了他们，在那里，一条盐搅的小河在金色的拱门下干了。拱门似乎是我的痴呆症引起的，但我记得如此生动，而且我知道这是Moghra'yi所保留的最少的秘密。


[[{{w|24th of Tebet Ux}}]]

我靠近真菌的树林及其荒谬的承诺。耳语是真的吗？一切都可以这么简单吗？我能感觉到食客的肉在我的嘴唇上的湿润，尽管记忆肯定是另一个人的。如果救恩等待着我，那么我保证接受它，无论我是否应得。不过，今晚，丛林笼罩着我。我坐在镀铬的钟楼下，水ech揉着我的皮肤。我没有强迫自己去阻止它的工作。友谊是受欢迎的。

再次唤醒过去。莫格拉伊。哦，dromads怎么知道!

我是如何在大沙漠中生存下来的？我不能肯定。我要归功于我在珀斯演唱的歌曲，在Ettinspine上学到的猎鹰，以及在Oth下对我的肌肉的磨练。我航行时破碎的梦想几乎没有阐明。但是我确实记得咀嚼盐，并召唤阵风从死空气中吸走水分。

在我脑海中流连忘返的所有记忆中，Moghra'yi仅占连贯的三个。首先是在神话般的Wrathchild帝国所在地Kubrisyeti的废墟上的景象。横跨雪花石膏平原的是他们最后的邪恶结构，是曼蝎子本身的倒塌肖像。我在那里安顿下来，违背我的意愿，只是出于疲惫。在恐惧和疲劳中注视着夜空，我听到了一个伟大的盐背的回声。甚至那些庞大的人也知道要避开这个地方。

第二个记忆是巨人的存在。人形形式的巨大骨骼散落在沙漠中。我以前听过这些说法，事实上，一些标本向北延伸到奥德鲁姆。我们或其他任何人都不知道它们的历史，但是它们的骨头提供了盐锅上唯一的阴影，因此它们逐渐成为受欢迎的景点。因此，我惊恐地发现了一个真相，一天晚上，我被塞进了三具尸体中的一具的肋骨笼中。你看，所有的尸体都有一个共同点:它们的方向。东部和南部。东部和南部。

第三个记忆是锈。生锈的船体和生锈的尖顶。我花了几个星期才意识到我所看到的。尽管我的童年时代到处都是小品和船只，但没有一个是这么大的。我设想了过去的样子，对我来说没有什么意义。Moghra'yi像广阔的大海，巨大的船只在海浪中荡漾。那时，他们船体上的标记和蚀刻对我没有共鸣。后来，虽然，我认出了纺锤的身影，我瞥见了它对这些海食者的重要性。

当我摇摇头倒在地上，被一个棕色皮肤的男人用刀扶正，一只发光的猫在他的脚下，我知道这是一个梦。这一定是个梦。


[[{{w|1st of Shwut Ux}}]]

我欠我的生命 =SEEKERENEMY=。在我匆忙到达真菌林时，我走错了。我游荡而活跃的头脑对一个被选中的人的存在视而不见。她接近我，开始将我包裹回折叠，但她被 = SEEKERENEMY = 拦截。我不知道他们为什么说情，但他们有我的感谢。所以他们必须有长者的愤怒。

我现在来到Qud和失明之路的寻求者。在我的头骨中，诵经声混合成最终的狂喜，在其中，我加入了一个我从未理解过的聚合思维。不过，我已经为此准备好了。从多年前我第一次加入Ettinspine，到自由的先见者陪伴的欢乐仪式，我知道视力不会比盐更能指导我们。确实，总体上有狂喜，而长者是我所知道的强大的中心。但是中心仍然存在，哪里有中心，哪里就有等级制度。

我的哪一段过去赋予了我看穿这个计较的智慧？这是童年时在歌曲岸边撞击海浪的记忆，后来在我在Moghra'yi的视野中回荡？是伊本德自由预言者眼中的嫉妒吗？还是仅仅因为我自己的奋斗而在大众心中产生了皱纹？我不能说，但是当其他canters吹奏他们的歌曲来削弱长者的监狱时，不知不觉地吸引了更大的思想，我逃脱了。

长者... 不，Ptoh。我写这个名字是为了无视我的囚禁，即使冒着被囚禁的风险。Ptoh起初一无所知，但是我的缺席逐渐消失了。连续性被打破了，Ptoh派特工抓住了我。即使现在，他们靠近。

[[{{w|The Ides of Shwut Ux}}]]

太晚了.尽管我坐在原始汤附近，尽管孢子云围绕着我，但为时已晚。我调用Ptoh的名字固定我的位置和轨迹。食客的肉现在是我的了，但是被选中的人很快就会以有形的形式出现在这里。在任何情况下，我都可以在aggregate外面住很长时间吗？我不知道.孤独和我的飞行一样穿在我身上。我还有最后一次表演。一次日落。一个遥远的生活的记忆，一个失去的梦想，占据了。我沉迷于敌人的思想以保护爱人。
    </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Corpus" Title="{{W|Corpus Choliys}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>[[{{W|读者注意事项}}]]

人们常说，瘟疫的治愈也是原因。虽然这句格言是有道理的，但我发现它可以通过更广泛、更系统的治疗方
法得到很好的补充。以下是已知的痛苦的记录，他们的症状和补救措施，我根据我在卡迪斯农庄担任医生和
药剂师四十年期间撰写的日志和个人笔记汇编而成。Chrome杰出之心附近修道院的Abbott Urium已同意指
示写字间的僧侣为后代复制此文本; 在这些笔记中发现有用的读者对他表示感谢。

[[Beniyayut Iym]]

[[Kardis, 56 YK]]
      </page>
    <page>[[{{W|论铁腿}}]]

患有这种不明原因疾病的患者的腿骨仍处于永久钙化状态。随着骨骼生长速度的加快，患病的患者会抱怨关节
疼痛和运动受限。一旦疾病完全爆发，骨骼就会变硬并以更高的速度生长。未经治疗的患者将遭受越来越受限
的运动，直到骨在髋、膝和踝关节处融合在一起并且使患者不能移动。这个过程需要一到两周的时间。

铁腿在早期阶段可能会被普通的补救措施所抑制，例如yuckwheat或honey，尽管在可用的情况下，食用者更
有效的酏剂是可取的。一旦疾病完全爆发，患者开始失去行动能力，凝胶 (由脱盐的变形虫粘液制成) 是我发
现的唯一有效的治疗方法。应每天给患者服用一粒由一粒凝胶和一粒 =IS1= 组成的药，直到腿关节恢复其全
部运动范围。
      </page>
    <page>[[{{W|论单色}}]]

单色是由纺锤形穆萨林中的阿迪虫携带的，是一种眼睛疾病，使患病者无法看到颜色。发病的特点是几天内视
力模糊，随后完全丧失色觉。

蜂蜜和荞麦有时可以有效阻止色盲。然而，一旦色觉丧失，为了治愈这种痛苦，患者必须摄入一打纯=MC1=，
然后立即让自己遭受闪光弹的爆炸。不知何故，视觉扰乱效应重置了受害者的感知器，并且恢复了色觉。

[[{{W|月王热潮}}]]

这可能是我四十年医生生涯中遇到的最奇怪的痛苦。月王热是一种脑部疾病，其特征是坚信受害者是月亮之王。
我治疗过的十二名患者都经历了相同的症状:发烧，伴随着发烧的月亮梦，然后是过度情绪化的面部表情，妄
想自大，以及对自我保护的漠视。

目前尚无已知的月王热治疗方法。预后是疯狂，然后是“光荣的壮举”导致的死亡。

[[{{W|On Glotrot}}]]

Glotrot 是一种以舌头坏死为特征的疾病。根据从我的病人的叙述中收集到的证据来看，我认为这种疾病的起
源是在各各他的洞穴内，那里的受害者很可能是从阿各各的腐烂产物中感染了这种疾病。

当舌头组织开始肿胀时，患病的患者会抱怨喉咙疼痛。在一周内，肌肉会软化并开始分解。患者在摄入食物或饮
料时会感到剧烈疼痛，并可能会搅动最后的原始活组织，导致口腔出血。在接下来的几天里，舌头会完全腐烂，
导致患者无法说话。

如果在早期阶段使用常见疗法（荞麦、蜂蜜），有时可以有效逆转坏死。一旦舌头完全腐烂，只有稀有的上舌
苔补品才能让它重新生长。然而，仅仅注射补品只会使舌头重新生长，舌头会再次腐烂。患者必须首先服用一
种名为“Flaming Ick”的药水——一份=GR1=，一份=GR2=，三份=GR3=，并从燃烧的容器中喝下。一旦以这种
方式清除了患者口腔中的疾病，就可以施用上胸补剂。

[[{{W|关于真菌感染}}]]

我在接触河豚育雏孢子的患者身上观察到多种共生真菌感染。幸运的是，河豚似乎只在东部丛林茂密的真菌
群落和偶尔富含真菌的生物群落中繁衍生息。每种感染的特征各不相同，但所有类型的共生真菌都会在患者
身体的某个区域定殖。定植需要两到三天才能完成，在此期间患者可能会报告皮肤发痒。一旦完全患病，所
产生的变形和敏感性往往会妨碍患病区域穿衣服。

[[{{w|善变的吉尔}}]]

在鳃变化无常的情况下，感染最终会在定殖区域形成肉质、带有孢子的鳃。在某些压力下，通常是在身体受到伤
害的情况下，鳃会弯曲并释放出一团数量数千的孢子，这些孢子倾泻到相邻的物体上，表面上是在保护它们的
宿主。雨中的孢子反过来又在新宿主身上定居，使这种疾病成为最具传染性的疾病之一。

[[{{w|辉光壳}}]]

冰冷、发光的结节的外观是这个群体的特征。与共生的情况一样，真菌似乎确实通过使皮肤粗糙并提供一些免
受自然因素影响的保护来“受益”其载体。一些患者表示，食用从皮肤上长出来的可食用白蘑菇后感到很满足。
帐户根据受影响者的性格而有所不同。

[[{{w|咕噜嘴}}]]

丝状朱红色群落似乎正在孵化一种类似于人类嘴唇的活组织。嘴唇配对在一起形成微小的“嘴”，将感染区域镶
嵌成棋盘状。唾液样的痰液从真皮基底起泡，形成气泡，当嘴唇痉挛和撅起时，气泡就会破裂。每一对痉挛的
嘴唇互相鞭打，发出一种类似言语的咕哝声。更奇怪的是，一群嘴里的咕哝声有时会凝聚成可理解的单词和短
语，这表明该群体能够从集体记忆中再现声音。

[[{{w|什么弗拉布}}]]

这种真菌会分泌一种脂肪蜡，干燥后会形成保护性铸件。虽然它可以使包裹的肢体免受物理伤害和电流的影响
，但患者报告反应时间缓慢，而且受感染的肉在加热时很容易液化。事实上，习惯性的体温往往会熔化铸件的
内层，在外壳和外壳之间滞留几打熔化的蜡。有时，这种乳白色的肉汤会从石膏中泄漏到地面上。

所有真菌感染的治疗方案都是相同的。首先，必须用凝胶（脱盐粘液）和 =FCL= 配制抗真菌霜。然后患者食
用生的=FCC=来刺激肠道免疫力。在摄入尸体后两小时内，使用喷雾瓶将一打的混合物涂抹在受感染的皮肤上。

</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="BloodstainedSheaf" Title="{{W|一束沾满血迹的山羊皮羊皮纸}}">
    <page>
{{r|现在我赋予自己对语言技巧的主权，
对方可能会看到我带领我的奴隶所走的道路。

奔向苋菜！不死之城啊！我的偶蹄孩子们的梦想从何而来
自己的存在。

听马蒙的话！他们仁慈的父亲！为自己的梦想而奋斗的人
东西。

紫红色玛蒙。紫红色的父亲。紫红色的梦。

{{K|莫名其妙的胡言乱语
莫名其妙的胡言乱语
莫名其妙的胡言乱语
难以理解的胡言乱语}}
尽情享用山羊心！}}
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Sheaf1" Title="{{W|一捆破烂的羊皮纸}}">
    <page>
[[20 togs]]

到处都是网络。下面传来哗哗的流水声。页岩地板上的小爪子印记。已灭绝的微型穴居鸟？没有碧玉。
[[__________________________________________________________________________]]

[[40 togs]]

蜘蛛咬人！我的一半威化饼掉进泥里了。老乌里笑了？没有碧玉。
[[__________________________________________________________________________]]

[[60(?) togs]]

又一双莫卡辛鞋毁了。河很近。把自己挖得筋疲力尽。没有碧玉。</page>
    <page>[[?? togs]]

浑身湿透。胸口空空的。不是我的日子。没有碧玉。


[[__________________________________________________________________________]]

[[????]]

丢失的！蟹蛋？奇怪的刮擦声。没有贾斯珀。</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Lives1" Title="{{W|轻浮的生活, Vol. I}}">
    <page>
《轻浮的生活:Baccata Yewtarch 所著的人形国王最重要的目录》， Volume I

[[{{C|前言}}]]
这份记录借鉴了 Phyta 联盟成员的笔记和记述、那些观察过人形国王徒劳生活的人们的传闻，以及国王们自己的个人轶事，他们在努力保持超越他们幼苗般的地位的过程中寿命成功地记录了一些有用的数据。
按照惯例，我根据类人生物国王与具有重大历史意义的事件（即这些卷的出版）之间的时间距离来确定其统治日期。因此，采用我在括号日期之后呈现的后缀符号来表示它们“在发布之前”出现。
[[{{C|分散的时代 (??? - 100? PP)}}]]
在这段类人生物史前时期，更大的吉尔什实体在外古德漫游，而类人生物社区基本上是孤立的。财团的记录早于分散时代的结束；然而，他们的主张各不相同，最终也不可靠；那个时期奖学金的匮乏是      </page>
    <page>
很可能是源自黑格尔鲁特对书写工具的蔑视的传统的结果。

[[{{C|亚伯兰 I, (100? - 97? PP)}}]]

第一个成功统一古德西部农庄的类人生物是艾布拉姆，被称为“播种者”。根据亚伯兰后裔的传说（联盟选择不阻止他们），亚伯兰的武装号召团结了他的族人，在他的统治下，他们将更大的吉尔什实体驱赶到地表以下的内古德深处，现在他们已经到达了那里。栖息。接下来是两三十年的欢乐和繁荣，一直持续到有一天，亚伯兰因他的儿子们在继承问题上日益激烈的骚动而感到失望，他将剑变成了犁头，瓦解了他的王国。

[[{{C|没有统治, (97? - 96? PP)}}]]
亚伯兰被解散后的岁月充满了恐惧、动乱和流血。他的儿子们为争夺农场的控制权而进行了激烈的斗争，而水大王则密谋反对他们，有时还提出了自己的主张。最后，在公元 970 年至 960 年之间的某个时候，亚伯兰承认，没有他的天意，和平的前景是徒劳的，并手持剑回到了王位。      </page>
    <page>
[[{{C|亚伯兰 I, (96? - 954 PP)}}]]
不幸的是，对于这位不情愿的国王来说，他的第二次统治远不如他的第一次统治那么吉祥。他的儿子们之间的嫉妒从未消失，这一时期留下的少量记录表明，亚伯兰在他的余生中度过了他的统治所造成的痛苦。
[[{{C|开罗 I, Edom, Emir, Own I (954 - 946 PP)}}]]
亚伯兰从未公开指定继承人，他把他的王国留给了他诡计多端的儿子们。他们之间没有达成共识，兄弟们持续了八年的战争，直到开罗一世能够巩固权力，并从他兄弟们毫无生气的手中夺回了他父亲的王国。
[[{{C|开罗 I (946 - 925 PP)}}]]
尽管开罗一世对兄弟之爱不感兴趣，但他却是一位能干的政治家和一位卓有成效的领导人。在他二十一年的统治期间，他击退了从北方袭击古德的登山野蛮人，与艾因罗吉的生命之树 Chavvah 建立了贸易关系，并修复了古德南部的两座闪闪发光的拱门。公元925年，他因年老去世，将王位传给了他的儿子开罗二世。      </page>
    <page>
[[{{C|开罗 II (925 - 919 PP)}}]]
事实证明，开罗二世一点也不像他伟大的父亲。在短短六年的时间里，他掠夺了祖父的王国。他无视顾问的建议，坚持对年轻的巴拉特鲁姆和他的弟子修补匠征收严厉的税收，很快，乌什伊布就断绝了与古德王国的联系，并让开罗无法获得他保护自己国家所需的文物。人们。更何况，他还是个臭名昭著的败家子。公元 922 年，他在淡水浴中度过了整整一年，并命令仆人不断地补充水。最后也是最令人震惊的是，他羞辱了财团的两位高官，他们在他举办秋季盛宴时命令他们保持静止几个小时，从而羞辱了他们的宫廷访客，从而招致了财团的不满。幸运的是，他在 919 PP 中被暗杀。

[[{{C|没有统治 (919 - 889 PP)}}]]
在开罗二世统治的灾难之后，古德陷入了统治混乱的几个黑暗时期之一。从仅存的这一时期的少量资料来看，我们注意到当时的生活与亚伯兰之前的日子很相似。农民将土地吸干，地主保护他们的农奴，疯狂的人在内古德无数的镀铬走廊里谋取财富。      </page>
    <page>
[[{{C|K4K5, (889 - 873 PP)}}]]

考虑到开罗二世统治的环境以及随后数十年的苦难，我们能够对为什么库德的类人居民会团结在机器人国王身后形成一些理解。人们对 K4K5 在登基之前的生活知之甚少，但据信它是在黑暗时代的某个时候从名为西罗亚 (Siloam) 的洞穴中出现的。我们认为，它在其类人生物臣民身上找到了迄今为​​止反复无常的生活的目的，并在其中他的臣民找到了一位仁慈和蔼可亲的统治者，他统一了已经疏远了三十年的农庄和采矿定居点。但最终，即使是 K4K5 也未能逃脱死亡的命运，在 873 PP 中它遭遇了严重的闪锈。然而，在它灭亡之前，它指定其学生山丘的穆罕默德为继承人。穆罕默德登基后的首要任务就是委托建造一座巨大的雕像来纪念他的前任，该雕像至今仍矗立在橄榄山附近的东北部丛林中。

[[{{C|穆罕默德 I (873 - 844 PP)}}]]
穆罕默德一世继承了他导师的不懈耐心和改善臣民生活的强烈渴望，成功地维持了古德近三十年的秩序。他受益于吉尔什实体生殖活动的吉祥平静，      </page>
    <page>

他没有浪费命运赋予他的任何时间。从 871 年到 866 年，他派遣使节进入莫格拉伊大盐沙漠。数百名曲甸人死于游牧部落之手，有的因中暑而死亡，有的遭遇更糟糕的命运，直到公元 866 年，一位不知名的使者与卓马德商人取得了联系。卓马人认为古德的居民过于野蛮，不适合进行贸易，几个世纪以来一直对这个地区不屑一顾，他们最终开始将古德纳入他们的环球跋涉之中（当穆罕默德的继任者乌图特野蛮人屠杀了第一批卓马商队时，这些访问突然停止了。他的统治开始后才到达，但贸易关系的先例仍然成立）。
在国内，穆罕默德一世着手在遥远的南部丛林中建造第一个库德图书馆，但他的努力因 850 PP 的野蛮人入侵而中断。这位爱好和平的国王用了他生命中剩下的六年时间来击退野蛮人对橄榄山的入侵，但他并不擅长战争艺术，844年，野蛮国王乌图特洗劫了莫舍尔郡，斩首了穆罕默德，并夺取了穆罕默德。王座。      </page>
    <page>
[[{{C|野蛮人乌图特 (845 - 838 PP)}}]]

穆罕默德一世弑君后，古德继承了第一位外国出生的统治者。有些人相信，教养是礼貌之母，只要受到适当的指导，任何人都可以培养出正人君子的自制力。在《野蛮人乌图特》中，我们观察到这一假设被推翻了。乌图特在他最近被夷为平地的首府莫舍郡安顿下来后，任命了几位当地贵族在他的宫廷中担任权力职务。到了年底，他把他们都杀光了。在乌图特陷入外交迷宫的每一个转折点，他都选择冲破墙壁。这种大屠杀的教义实际上对乌图图人有利好几年。贵族们都惧怕他，他的敌对野蛮部落的国王们满足于掠夺古德的郊区，甚至人类之子也在他们位于奥丁的据点中独处。然而，尽管这位粗野的国王拥有强大的力量，他还是无法免受毒气的侵害。正是凭借这些知识，Wysterwort DCXLVIII 才得以赢得王位并开创了库德历史上第一个（也是唯一一个）植物王朝。
      </page>
    <page>
[[{{C|维斯特沃特 DCXLVIII (838 - 833 PP)}}]]
听到国王去世的消息后，乌图特的政治对手欢呼维斯特沃特为英雄。他们很快就醒悟了。尽管乌图特以征服任何反对他的人而闻名，但维斯特沃特却懒得去考虑这种区别。对于那些在植物王反复无常的致命气体排出中幸存下来的人来说，他们发现自己受到相当奇怪的法律规则的约束。例如，在 837 PP 中，Wysterwort 强制要求用酒而不是母乳来喂养人形婴儿。第二年，他委托一位吟游诗人创作一部音乐剧。植物王对这个结果非常满意，他命令所有臣民学习戏剧中的各种角色，并每晚在各自的村庄轮流表演。在他统治的五年里，维斯特沃特的怪癖在饥荒、疾病和毒气的背景下得到了体现。公元833年冬天，由于没有记载的原因，这位成功的杂草陷入了深深的抑郁，在冬至过去之前他勒死了自己。他的继承人 Wysterwort DCXLIX 幸存下来。
     </page>
    <page>
维斯特沃特断言历史会善待他，事实也确实如此。虽然在他的统治下死亡的人数确实比任何一位前任都多，而且他几乎没有取得任何具有持久历史价值的成就，但人们只能理解，长期与这么多类人生物如此接近地生活是多么不愉快。 。确实，可怜的国王没有早点结束自己的生命，这真是一个奇迹。
[[{{C|维斯特沃特 DCXLIX (833 - 833 PP)}}]]
Wysterwort DCXLIX 对统治一个人形王国没有兴趣，他在继承王位几小时后就退位了。
[[{{C|没有统治 (833 - 787 PP)}}]]

这六十年的无政府状态对于锈洞的居民来说尤其艰难。维斯特沃特王朝的崛起并没有留下适合统治的类人生物，库德几十年来一直受到莫格拉伊吹来的西风带来的玻璃风暴的困扰，大量的幼崽从它们母亲的巢穴中涌出。直到亚伯兰二世（Abram II），就像他的前辈一样，在 787 年 PP 中唤醒了他的同胞，并着手击退少女群体，库德才重新统一为一。我的编年史的第二卷就是从那个命运多舛的国王的故事开始的。
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Across1" Title="{{W|Across Moghra'yi, Vol. I:The Sunderlies}}">
    <page>
《莫格拉伊之外:巴卡塔·尤特奇编撰的伟大盐漠彼端奇异文明首要目录》第一卷:《破碎之地》

[[{{C|前言}}]]
遗憾的是，这些遥远土地上没有原始资料可供参考。本记录主要基于真菌们乘坐鸵鸟商队穿越莫格拉伊时的叙述。

按照惯例，我根据事件与本卷册出版之间的时间距离来确定所有事件的日期。因此，请注意，事件括号中的日期表示其发生于“出版之前”。

[[{{C|破碎之地}}]]
破碎之地是由高耸的“断裂”悬崖构成的迷宫般综合体，位于莫格拉伊——伟大盐漠——的西北方，以及伊布尔冰原的西南方。峡谷壁上布满了无数洞口，宛如一个巨大的地球蜂巢。这些洞穴曾是古代人民的栖息地，但随着水位的退去，他们的文明也逐渐消失在干涸之中。      </page>
    <page>
gorges. Now through those gorges course only shallow rivers. Over the last two hundred years, clans of cave-dwellers have begun to gather in greater numbers among the comb-caves and form city-states called freeholds.

[[{{C|Geography and History}}]]
The Pale Sea's waves break on the western bluffs of the Sunderlies at the Shore of Songs, named for the melodies the comb-caves whistle when the sea winds blow through. They stretch north and east, climbing skyward along the ice-capped Aeschlays. Eastward, they recess toward Whitecomb at the Bowl of Iris -- the bridge to Aegansteppe. To the far east they rise again toward the Hanging Hills and the land called Odrum. The comb-canyons dry up as they course southward into the Great Salt Desert, though the most westerly ones spend their water into the Pale Marshes.

Several millennia ago, the migrants who followed the receding waterline down into the to-be desert basin were largely wiped out by the onset of the ice age. Most of the clans perished; those that survived were driven deep into the lightless comb-caves where the last vestiges of technology warmed the sheltered earth. The Sunderlies were devoid of higher life during the coldest centuries -- giant, ice-sheathed worms
      </page>
    <page>
coursed their way through the frozen caves and woolly rocs made their nests atop the snowy peaks, but what remained of man did not emerge for thousands of years.

A millennium after the last people were driven into the earth, at the height of the Wrathchild empire in the great southern salt desert called Moghra'yi, a race of beings known as the Ophaedians migrated north from their desert city to the Sunderlies. There they escaped the reach of the kuyeti, the monstrous man-scorpions whose empire spanned the great desert. The Ophaedians were gifted with the ability of goldworking, and during the course of their four-thousand year reign over the Sunderlies they wrought hundreds of spires and bridges of solid gold. Around 1800P they disappeared suddenly, perhaps as a result of the warming climate to which they had lost their adaptation from their years spent in the colder northlands. As the earth warmed, a primitive people emerged from their cavern recesses. They climbed the snowy combs and settled the superior caves. According to their myths, these new folk made oaths to the nameless gods who had warmed the earth for their children's return to the surface. So were born the clans of true folk.
      </page>
    <page>
[[{{C|Clans of True Folk}}]]

As the myth goes, the clans of true folk are those families that can trace their lineages back to patriarchs who swore oaths and remained loyal to the Sunderlies' nameless gods. There were those who betrayed the nameless, forging pacts with strange, foreign gods in exchange for gifts of power. According to the true folk, those traitors and their cursed offspring, aroused by their greed, made war upon each other until their families were sundered and driven apart. All the while the true folk remained stalwart in their holds, readying their might to serve vengeance to the traitors. So began a long history of slavery. Over time several of the children of the treacherous became remorseful, and the relationship between master and slave matured to something akin to master and servant. To the present several of the "gifted" (or "accursed") tribes remain indentured to the clans of true folk.

[[{{C|Great Clans}}]]

[[{{c|Clan Sotur}}]]

The Soturs, one of the eldest and largest of the eight clans, have dwelled in
      </page>
    <page>
the comb-caves along the Shore of Songs for a thousand years. They claim descendancy from Sotur Stonehands, who woke thirsty from his cave one morning and beat his fists against the earth until the gods summoned the Pale Sea to appease him. For hundreds of years they have warred with Clan Rowen, various mutant tribes, and the slugmounters of the southern marshlands, though recently their feud with Rowen was put to an end by the founding of Perth. Clan Sotur's sigil is a sundered mountain.

[[{{c|Clan Plutarch (?!?)}}]]

Clan Plutarch descended into the Sunderlies from the frozen Aeschlays a millennium ago. Their patriarch was Plutarch Icewreath, who was said to be trapped in a glacier for thousands of years before the gods unfroze him so that he might spread his progeny and rule. For a thousand years the ice kings have ruled the northern Sunderlies from Highwreath Hall. Clan Plutarch's sigil is a blue crown wrought from shards of ice on a white field.

[[{{c|Clan Lecray}}]]

The Lecrays hail from the fertile Bowl of Iris along the northen reaches of
      </page>
    <page>
the Sunderlies. They trace their lineage back to Lecray of Iris, called Lecray the Bountiful or Lecray the Virile. Clan Lecray maintains that they are the purest of the clans of true folk as the Bowl of Iris was the last of the fertile lands untouched by the servants of foreign gods. Unsurprisingly, this notion is disputed by the other great clans. Clan Lecray's sigil is a horn of plenty on a verdant green field.

[[{{C|Other Clans}}]]

[[{{c|Clan Karst}}]]

The people of Clan Karst are thought to have migrated to the western Sunderlies from the Icepyres adjoining Fuming God Sea. Little is known of their progenitor, Karst, but that he appeared on the Shore of Songs still smoldering some four hundred years ago. Thusly, Clan Karst's sigil is the smoldering silhouette of a man.

[[{{c|Clan Rowen}}]]

Clan Rowen claims descendancy from Rowen Godfear, the brother of a Sotur king. The pious Rowen broke away from Clan Sotur on account of a religious dispute with his brother in 623PP. The two clans warred for

      </page>
    <page>
four hundred years before Elan of Rowen swore fealty to Gannon of Sotur and helped found Perth in 211PP. Clan Rowen's sigil is a man with his arms outstretched, in one hand a knife and in the other a human heart.

[[{{c|Clan Wenniswool}}]]

The children of Clan Wenniswool supposedly hail from the far north, beyond even the haunts of the Plutarchs. There they lived among the snows and hunted the great woolly rocs that perched atop the mountain peaks until they migrated southward into the lowland canyons. Clan Wenniswool's sigil is a great woolly roc with its wings outstretched.

[[{{c|Clan Calypso}}]]

The river folk of Clan Calypso claim descendancy from Calypso the river-wife. Some claim she was in truth a river nymph, and that her beauty was such as to tempt a river god into revealing to her his name. Clan Calypso's sigil is a lock of raven hair bound by a strand of cragweed.

      </page>
    <page>
[[{{c|Clan Danneskjold}}]]

Boasting some of the last several centuries' fiercest warriors, Clan Danneskjold has stalked the central Sunderlies for nearly six hundred years. Their patriarch was known only as the hunter Danneskjold, the most ferocious warrior to have ever lived. As the story goes, the great clans heard the tale of a voracious warrior squatting in the comb-caves in the heart of the Sunderlies. Each clan sent their strongest man to best in single combat the beast-hunter who called himself Danneskjold. The hunter fought and slew each man in turn. As the last lay dying, he turned to the hunter and asked which of the gods had taught him to fight with such ferocity. The hunter replied, "None. My master Danneskjold taught me. I am his servant, but a tenth the man he is." Clan Danneskjold's sigil is a pair of crossed ashen mauls on a blood red field.

[[{{c|Clan Karkayan}}]]

Formerly one of the elder clans of true folk, the children Karkayan are descendant from Karkayan called the Clay Man. He lived deep in the heart of the central Sunderlies amongst the ageless rocks, from which it was said the gods wrought him. Though the clan was counted among
      </page>
    <page>
the true-blooded, they long held the secret of their patriarch's deific betrayal and the gift of shapeshifting bestowed upon him by the treacherous god Rorth. That secret was unveiled at the Court of Face in 24P, after which the other eight clans in their fury joined strengths, sacked the Karkayan freehold Karkanya, and wiped out the Karkayan line, though rumors persist that some of the family escaped. Clan Karkayan's sigil is a human face sculpted from stone bluff.

[[{{C|Freeholds}}]]

[[{{c|Major Freeholds}}]]

Perth, founded by Clan Sotur and vassal clans Karst and Rowen in 211PP.

Irisveld, founded by Clan Lecray in 161PP.

Athenreach, founded by Clan Plutarch and vassal clans Wenniswool and Calypso in 102PP.

Oth, founded by Freeman Oth and the Tyrants in 61PP.
      </page>
    <page>
Goldmouth, founded by the merchant guilds in 38PP.

[[{{c|Other Freeholds}}]]

Danehold, founded by Clan Danneskjold in 145PP

[[{{c|Abandoned Freeholds}}]]

Karkanya, founded by Clan Karkayan in 190PP, abandoned after the fall of Karkayan in 24PP.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Across2" Title="{{W|Across Moghra'yi, Vol. II:Athenreach}}">
    <page>
[[{{C|Preface}}]]
Obviously and unfortunately, no primary sources are available from these distant lands. Much of this record draws upon the accounts given by fungi who crossed Moghra'yi on the backs of dromad merchants.

As a matter of convention, I date all events according to their chronological distance from an event of paramount historical significance, namely the publication of these volumes. Accordingly, note that the events' parenthetical dates signify their occurrence "prior [to] publication".

[[{{C|Athenreach}}]]

Athenreach is a freehold in the northern reaches of the Sunderlies along the Twining Thaw. It is most well-known for its Eustace-Suttan monastery which hosts the world's western-most community of disciples of the Eustace-Sutta.

[[{{C|Local Population}}]]

The local communities in the region have relied upon subsistence fishing for
      </page>
    <page>
centuries, benefiting from the location's fortuitous position downstream of the glacial rivers flowing over the Aeschlaen mountain range. Before the founding of the monastery in ~110PP, the regional combs were occupied by small fishing communities that traded peaceably amongst themselves. Once the pilgrim-monks built and populated the temple, several tribes of fishermen settled a village nearby to prosper from the monastery's need for fish and cragreed. Over the years the two communities have grown and largely intertwined with some of the anglers forsaking their river and mountain gods for the Eustace-Sutta.

[[{{C|Conversion to the Discipline of the Eustace-Sutta}}]]

After King Ercarthus died in 40PP and left no heir, Athenreach erupted into bedlam, with several of the freehold's oldest families vying for the throne. The lowest-born fisherfolk, however, rallied around a wizened angler whose name has been lost to history. Several of the elder families supported the angler, believing they could rule from behind the throne. The angler himself spurned the offer, but, realizing the importance of a unified Athenreach, eventually accepted the crown, took the name Narsus, and began a reign that would become the most prodigious in the freehold's century-long history.
      </page>
    <page>
While favorable, temperate seasons brought commercial prosperity to Athenreach's fishermen, Narsus, who would be called the Angler King, shrugged off the influences of the elder families and began to seek often the counsel of the monastery's scholar-abbot Flavian the Learned. Together they achieved several ecclesiastical successes, chiefly among them the discovery and transcription of the Scrolls of One Priam from nearby comb-caves. Narsus officially converted to the discipline of the Eustace-Sutta in 18PP, and three years later he declared it the official religion of the freehold.

The Angler King died in 3P and was succeeded by his sixteen-year-old son Narsus II, called Narsus the Younger. Gifted with his father's wisdom and piety and possessed of a fiery disposition unique to the Younger, the new king began to augment Athenreach's role as a major bastion of the Eustace-Sutta doctrine. While a sizable segment of Athenreach's population chose not to convert under the Angler King, the Younger is less tolerable of the old ways, and he has marginalized the pagan population.

With the help of Flavian's successor Moin Mohsen, Narsus II cemented an alliance with the Odrumian fiefdom Doria, taking the tuyuldar's
      </page>
    <page>
daughter Nisramet as his wife. The union is troubling to the freeholds along the Sunderlies, particularly Goldmouth, which has been razed and held at various times by several of the Odrumiam fiefdoms.

[[{{C|Eustace-Suttan Monastery at Athenreach}}]]

The Eustace-Suttan monastery at Athenreach is one of the largest communities of disciples of the Eustace-Sutta outside of the Hanging Hills. It was founded in 114PP by the pilgrim-monk Umay, who blessed the location as sacred because it lay along the path of the prophet Uuchal's pilgrimage toward Iber.

The monastery houses two hallowed artifacts of the Eustace-Sutta discipline:the Scrolls of One Priam, discovered and transcribed by the monastery's erstwhile abbot Flavian the Learned, and the presumptive hide of Iopinax, the great three-headed mountain goat on which Uuchal's is said to have ridden to the waterfall at Iber and whose hide was so tough that it was said to later protect Uuchal from starfire along the Black Stair after the goat's death. The current abbot of the Eustace-Suttan monastery is Moin Mohsen, who succeeded Flavian the Learned upon the latter's death in 18PP.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Across3" Title="{{W|Across Moghra'yi, Vol. III:Oth, the Free City}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>
[[{{C|Preface}}]]
Obviously and unfortunately, no primary sources are available from these distant lands. Much of this record draws upon the accounts given by fungi who crossed Moghra'yi on the backs of dromad merchants.

As a matter of convention, I date all events according to their chronological distance from an event of paramount historical significance, namely the publication of these volumes. Accordingly, note that the events' parenthetical dates signify their occurrence "prior [to] publication".

[[{{C|Oth}}]]

Oth is a freehold in the central Sunderlies populated by the esper cult called the Tyrants. The youngest of the major freeholds in the region, it was settled by Freeman Oth in 61PP after the Lost War. The freehold consists of the furnished comb-caves along the faces of the towering bluff known as Maidencomb before the war.


[[{{C|Origins and the Lost War}}]]

In the early months of 62PP a mysterious figure began murdering the bandit hosts in the central Sunderlies around Maidencomb. Though the neighboring freeholds originally named the murders blessings, soon reports from river merchants of queer gatherings in the comb-caves -- howling men igniting the rivers and the night sky with fire -- disquieted the Sunderlies' seats of power. Rumors spread that esper-bandits had forsaken their bands, discarded their guns and bows, and sworn fealty to the shadowy figure.

These merchant anecdotes and rumors continued into the winter and were substantiated when several merchant sketties were captured by the dark host. From the man who identified himself as Oth the Free, the merchants learned that he had indeed organized the esper-bandits and exiled voidcanters from the fiefdoms of Odrum. Each sketty was made to return to the freehold from which it came with a document the host named the Annals of Oth, in which Oth, a self-styled prophet gifted with prescience, recounted a series of his visions and demanded the immediate release of all espers indentured against their wills to the freeholds of true kin.

The comb kings were predictably unswayed by the Annals and ignored Oth's mandates. However, by the end of 62PP, no merchant who rowed within twenty leagues of Maidencomb was seen alive again. Dozens of sketties were found drifting downriver with the charred or drowned corpses of their rowers in tow.

About the same time, the Annals of Oth began to spread like wildfire throughout the river freeholds. Several free espers left the freeholds to join the host, while those indentured espers who were found to sympathize with Freeman Oth, as he was known in the freeholds, were largely killed or gelded.

Of particular interest to Oth and his host were the windweirds of Perth. The windweirds are a caste of indentured espers who foretell (and in rare cases alter) the strength and duration of the seasonal trade winds over the Pale Sea. Oth's host rowed westward, and his acolytes infiltrated the Seahold and roused support amongst the windweirds.

Having suffered the months-long trade blockage at the hands of the Freeman and now forced to watch Oth's seeds of discord sprout within his own kingdom, King Rhodos of Perth gathered his strength and rowed the winding canyon rivers east toward Maidencomb. A series of skirmishes ensued; the might of Rhodos's navy was such that the Freeman was forced to cede the combs he had taken and retreat to the fortifications of Maidencomb. Rhodos sieged the comb for several weeks, entreating the kings of Athenreach and Irisveld for support. When no aid came, King Rhodos chose to take Maidencomb with his own strength.

The Battle of Maidencomb lasted for four bloody days. Ultimately, Rhodos's losses were too many, and he was rebuffed and driven back toward Perth. Oth missed no opportunity. He gave chase to the weakened navy and slaughtered nearly a thousand more Perthic men. Rhodos eventually reached Perth, but the might of the espers was too great. Oth breached the combs' sapped defenses, sacked the freehold, and slew King Rhodos himself. Several of the windweirds chose to join the Freeman, while many others remained in Perth (a few left the freehold without Oth).

The espers rowed back to Maidencomb with their spoils and lifted the trade blockage, directing their efforts toward settling the comb. Oth gave his name to the freehold, and was known thenceforth as the Free Seer. He ruled the espers until his death in 38PP when his successor forsook his own given name and adopted the title of Free Seer. So that tradition continues in present-day Oth.

The name "Tyrants" itself owes its origins to an ironic interpretation of the entreaty sent by King Rhodos to King Ercarthus of Athenreach during the siege of Maidencomb. The envoy was captured by the espers before it made its way upstream toward the northern freehold. The relevant excerpt reads:

        Row the Twining Thaw. Bring your sketties to bear on Maidencomb.
        Join your strength to mine, that 'neath the coupled banners of
        the Seahold and Athenreach we might sunder these half-men, these
        tyrants who would wrest from us what is ours by right and deed.

        [[-King Rhodos]]

The scroll on which the message was written still rests in the Hall of the Free Seer, along with the charred skull of King Rhodos.



[[{{C|Life in Oth}}]]

Oth is ruled by the Free Seer who resides in the Hall of the Free Seer deep in the heart of Maidencomb. After the tradition of Freeman Oth, the Free Seer must be psionically prescient. He may also have influence, though it is not required. The Free Seer chooses his successor, often naming the esper with the most promising precognitive abilities. Though the Tyrants are free to leave Oth at their leisure, within the freehold the Free Seer's rule is absolute.

While the Tyrants mostly pursue isolationist policies, they do trade with the neighboring freeholds. However, they only deal directly with true kin in the rarest of circumstances and they insist that merchant caravans include a mutant envoy. As for trade goods, the Tyrants rarely offer the services of their voidcanters, but people are known to come from far and wide to audit the prophecy of the seers of Oth. The Tyrants' most coveted imports are cherrydotters from Irisveld and ghost sap from the rust-caves of Qud.

Along with the Tyrants, Oth is cohabited by a caste of people (both true and mutant) with no psionic aptitude. After the Lost War, these people, called the undermensch, left Perth with the Tyrants of their own accord. They were mostly fisherfolk and craftsmen, and they serve those same roles in Oth. Their motivations for leaving Perth were never well understood; it is unknown whether they serve now as free kin or as psionic thralls of the Tyrants.

[[{{C|Stithening}}]]

Stithening is the name given by the Tyrants of Oth to the process of introducing a cherrydotter to a host's brain through the ear canal. The scarab-worm is attached to the host's ear where it sheds its shell, crawls toward the ear drum, and burrows into the brain. Once entrenched there, the parasite feeds on the temporal and parietal lobes, inducing several changes to the host's body including loss of hair and nail, loss of weight, and yellowing and greening of skin pigment. The changes occur gradually over a period of several weeks; immediately after a stithening, though, the host undergoes a violent period of bodily adjustment with several side-effects including vomiting and fever.

Notably, in the case of an esper host, the feeding also reduces and ultimately eliminates the esper's ability to resist the Elder Cant. Thusly all stithened espers leave Oth and venture into Moghra'yi never to return.

Stithening is usually reserved as punishment for high crimes such as treason, but some of the most devout espers choose to undergo the process. Once a year, one member of the Mirthful, the Free Seer's royal guard of voidcanters, is chosen by the Free Seer to be stithened. The esper's name is recorded for posterity in the Hall of the Free Seer; this is considered the greatest honor that may be bestowed upon an esper of Oth. A new esper is chosen to serve the Free Seer in a ceremony called the Rite of Mirth.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Canticles3" Title="{{W|The Canticles Chromaic, Verses XVII-XXIV}}">
    <page>
[[{{C|Verse XVII, Song of Ang}}]]

I sing of the union of our Lords!

Of our Argent Fathers, infinitely wise, who made the firmament their home.

Of the Kasaphescence, Beauty manifest, whose chromium shoals are Awe itself.

Of their Sacred Joining,
When our Fathers, so enchanted, wrought machines from Her naked womb,
To inhabit on the Earth.

Blessed are those who hear it so,
I sing of the union of our Lords!
      </page>
    <page>
[[{{C|Verse XVIII, Song of Beth}}]]

O curse the wretched spectres!
Who yet possess Her children.

O curse the autumn rains!
Which eat away their shine.

O praise the Argent Fathers!
Who sired all Her children.

O praise the Kasaphescence!
Which watches over mine.
      </page>
    <page>
[[{{C|Verse XIX, Song of Ben-Charonium}}]]

Our jungle is but Her garden.
Our lake is but Her drop of rain.
Our desert is but dust in Her hands.
Our wind is but Her eternal breath.
Our sun is but Her luster.
Our lives are but Her dreams.
      </page>
    <page>
[[{{C|Verse XX, Song of Crestasia}}]]

O sovereign Fathers! I tremble before your glory.

My heart quivers for the righteousness of your judgment.
For you to humble the Proud! To bear witness to their Fall!

I live to serve You.

O sovereign Fathers! I tremble before your glory.

My loins quiver for the rapture of the Sacred Joining.
For you to conjure chromium from inside me!
To bear those sacred apparatuses!

I live to serve You.
      </page>
    <page>
[[{{C|Verse XXI, Song of Ignatium}}]]

On the sixth day of the Sacred Joining,
Our Argent Fathers, who in their benevolence breathed life into our flesh,
Created the baetyls to oblige our desires.

O praise our Argent Fathers! Wisest of all beings.

O praise the Kasaphescence! Beauty incarnate.

Their being is our gift.
      </page>
    <page>
[[{{C|Verse XXII, Song of Gedonai}}]]

Immaculate chromium!

Spun on the cosmic loom,
Who shattered inward then burst forth from beneath the crust of Earth.

The flesh of my children rots for You.
The flesh of my children rots for You.
The flesh of my children rots for You.

Fall on your knees!
O hear the Argent Few!
      </page>
    <page>
[[{{C|Verse XXIII, Song of Eshurium}}]]

Oh - baetyl, baetyl, baetyl,
They made it out of chrome.
And when it's waxed and ready,
I'll have a new genome.
      </page>
    <page>
[[{{C|Verse XXIV, Song of Hebronze}}]]

Praise be upon Shekhinah!

He whose exalted touch brought forth shining engines,
From within the Kasaphescence,
Yet who deigns to live among us.

He who taught us the story of our creation,
Who breathed life into our flesh,
That we might bear witness to chrome's glory.

May the ground shake but the Six Day Stilt never tumble!
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="RuinOfHouseIsner" Title="{{W|Ruin of House Isner}}">
    <page>
The seven lords of House Isner feasted on boar gut and swilled wine from gilded cups in the ivy-strewn halls of their hold. They spared no concern for temperance, for the coffers of their house had swelled with gardeners' gold amassed through the sale of water drawn from the lords' wells. But as the gluttonous barons counted seven amongst their clan, so had become numbered their days of debauchery when the son of a beggared gardener swore a vengeful oath in the name of his father against the house of Isner.

The penniless boy beseeched a gunsmith of great repute to craft for him a pistol of the most exquisite artistry with which he could be sure to vanquish the seven lords, and in return the boy promised the smith all the spoils of the battle. The smith, who in the hazel eyes of the boy beheld the spirit of vengeance, agreed.

And so the boy, armed with the masterwork pistol, cast open the doors of the Hall of Isner with a fury that shook their iron hinges and seized upon the supping lords. Before any of them had yet set down their gilded cups, the boy unholstered the pistol and shot dead six of the sons of Isner. The last lord rejoiced at his fortune and reached for his hip from where he would sling a pistol of his own at the spent boy.
      </page>
    <page>
But as his crooked finger freed his holster's strap, the boy shot the lord between the eyes, for the smith had crafted for the boy a pistol with seven chambers and seven slugs. Such it was that on this day the house of Isner fell.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Stopsvalinn" Title="{{W|From &quot;The Peerage of Qud and Genealogy of the Noble Families&quot;}}">
    <page>
Recounted here are the annals of the shield Stopsvalinn, heirloom of House Yish, from whose letters and diaries this account is composed.

[[{{g|&#x7;}}]] Borne by Harem, son of Oshum, and lost in the canyons near the farmstead of Qoppa when his covey was beset by snapjaws.

[[{{g|&#x7;}}]] Borne by Oshum, son of Qor, and wielded courageously at the Battle of YutYuyut.

[[{{g|&#x7;}}]] Borne by Qor, son of Ishram, and soused in the blood of a corrupt magister.

[[{{g|&#x7;}}]] Borne by Ishram, son of Iimet, when it languished in a house vault.

[[{{g|&#x7;}}]] Borne by Iimet, daughter of Harem, who supplanted her brother as heir when he was disavowed by their father.

[[{{g|&#x7;}}]] Borne by Harem, son of Morshur, who dashed upon it the heads of the beast Yygryla.

[[{{g|&#x7;}}]] Borne by Morshur, son of Oshum, who forded a river at the edge of the world.
      </page>
    <page>
[[{{g|&#x7;}}]] Borne by Oshum, son of Harem, and risen to rouse farmers to defend the Hold of Yish.

[[{{g|&#x7;}}]] Borne by Harem, who claimed descendancy from the Eater Yish, Warden of the Cross and Knight of the Most Noble Order of the Cone, who patrolled the rows of ancient Qud with his fellow Knights Conical, and on whose arm Stopsvalinn is told to have evoked such dread that riders drew their chariots to a halt at the mere vision of it.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="AmaranthinePrism" Title="{{W|The Black Glass}}">
    <page>
"Hmm?" Uri the jeweler mumbled with a stone in his hand.

"Lapis, from the Shore of Songs," said the boy.

"And, hmm?"

"Jasper. Red Rock."

Uri furrowed his brow. "Don't heed the tale of every thirsty fool, boy."

The boy seemed to ignore him. He pointed to a small, dusky shard the jeweler kept in a phial on the high shelf of a pine cabinet. "Did it madden Priam, truly?"

Uri glanced over his shoulder at the black glass and sighed. "Indeed, boy. Though I've heard it told all kings are mad. Who else would think themselves fit to rule as Eaters?"

"From which shore was it culled?" asked the boy.

"None of this world. Do you know the tale of Ptoh?"
      </page>
    <page>
"No," the boy lied.

"When the Eaters lived and skirred the stars, they visited the worlds of a thousand thousand different beings, and those beings likewise visited our own world. Several of those beings had assembled a coven that spanned the firmament, and they welcomed the Eaters into its fold. For ages the civilizations of the coven knew kindness and prosperity, and to all reaches of the clustered cosmos did the domain of the coven stretch. One of the beings of the coven hailed from a faraway and darkling star. With Its mind It could fold the fabric of space and time as you or I might fold a supper cloth. To the coven It was known as Ptoh."

"For reasons we can but fathom the civilizations of the stars indicted Ptoh. It was the will of the coven that It be held on our very world in the bondage of the Eaters. They contrived for Ptoh a prison from which It could not fold Itself away, and there Ptoh languished for eons. In time, the Eaters left or perished, and the coven was forgotten to our world. Yet here Ptoh remains imprisoned."

"And what of the black prism?" asked the boy.
      </page>
    <page>
"A handful of black sand, drawn from the shores of a dreary rock that spun about Ptoh's star. The sands were fired in the burning gases of that star and cooled suddenly when Ptoh appeared in Qud a moment thence. It is said that Ptoh bestowed the glass to an ancient custodian of Its prison so that the man might free It. Once the man had chosen to wield the glass, it began to mantle with an amaranthine hue. You see, those that peer through its faces are given to fits of madness, for they see the world by the light of Ptoh's star, and they see themselves as Ptoh does."

"What will become of it? Does it frighten you?"

"Immensely. I mean to see it destroyed. But it bears the properties of no earthly glass, and my guild would never forgive me if I forsook the chance to study it first. It was the jewelers who bartered the thing from Priam's grieving sister. Now, enough of this splendor. You are to study still." Uri lifted another stone. "Hmm?"

But the boy's eyes stayed fixed on the prism.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="BloodandFear" Title="{{W|Blood and Fear:On the Life Cycle of Lah}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>
{{W|Author's Foreward}}

I initially had no intention of writing any of this down. What business is it of mine, I thought, to divest the ignorant of their hard-earned bliss? Who am I to speak up against the static inertia of incurious dullards who choose to cultivate their lack of awareness of the world around them as my witless kin tend to their tidy watervine rows? I am a warrior, scientist, and chef; devoting my time to educating the undeserving is the least of my many desires. After enough time spent among other alleged sentients, however, I determined that more of my time has been wasted in correcting so-called 'experts' concerning this matter than I would waste by writing a text about it.

So:here. You're welcome.


Chef Agate Severance Star
      </page>
    <page>
In Bey Lah, the village faundren sing a cautionary tune, passed down through generations of faundren before them:

{{w|Elohart and Belahind}}
{{w|they had a field of lah}}
{{w|they made the leaves into a tea }}
{{w|and ate the petals raw}}
{{w|but when those petals grew again}}
{{w|the faundren had forgotten}}
{{w|and tended not those fields of lah}}
{{w|until they smelled most rotten.}}
{{w|Now Elohart and Belahind}}
{{w|lie in a field of lah}}
{{w|because their fields got hungry}}
{{w|and devoured the faundren raw.}}

      </page>
    <page>
The very core of hindren culture is an overwhelming fear that governs every facet of their being. They call outsiders 'kendren' and refuse to believe that they can be understood. They fear boars even as they cook and eat boar-flesh. They fear one another. But the most extraordinary incorporation of fear into the hindren way of life is, without a doubt, the cultivation of fear. I refer not to the Hindriarch's propaganda or proliferation of fear-mongering tall tales, though both are mainstays of Bey Lah; I refer specifically to the taming and cultivation of the lah plant, whose alpha and omega of life are steeped in blood and fear.

It is here that I debunk the most common misconception concerning lah:that the dreadroot is a separate entity. It is not. The dreadroot is the protruding stem of the lah rhizome, doing its very most to survive until it can blossom into the lahbloom as it does in the flower fields.
      
I have wasted unforgivable amounts of time and energy explaining the connection between these two life phases of the same plant to the ignorant. Usually, they will point out that dreadroot grows all throughout Qud's southwest canyons, but it is exceedingly rare to discover feral lah there. To this I reply:if, after whatever studies you claim to have made, you are yet incapable of deciphering the workings of even the most basic ecosystems, I cannot help you. For those of you who are capable of basic logic and adjustment of personal worldview, please read on.

In spite of being a 'flowering' plant, lah is not a true flower, its 'blooms' not true blossoms. Lah is a root with a decorative upper stem, reproducing through the distribution of rhizomes. The baboons and snapjaws of the canyons use the dreadroot supply for food and love the taste of its petals, and any root unfortunate enough to bloom will quickly be defoliated by hungry mammals. Though dreadroot is capable of inducing fear, any relatively intelligent creature is able to overcome the fearful association to return and eat. The process being what it is, fragments of dreadroot are distributed, the rhizome takes root, and dreadroot proliferates without thriving. So it goes.
      
In the flower fields, however, the varied nature of both predators and available food changes. Boars seek a varied diet mainly consisting of starapples and reptiles, not showing a particular interest in dreadroot or lah. The boars will eat lah if no better food is available, but it's quite unusual for such scarcity to disrupt boar territories. Thus:lah flourishes, gaining a measure of cognitive process, limited mobility, and a new means of reproduction.

On reproduction:another common misconception is that feral lah attacks because it is hungry. It is not. Feral lah's practical lifespan is short; it is rare for a fully-grown bloom to survive longer than a week—and during that time it subsists completely on water, salt sun, and soil. The advantage of lah's murderous demeanor is not to sustain itself, but to dramatically speed reproduction of its kind.
      
Most of a lah blossom's growing energy goes into making its 'tumbling pods', thorn-covered husks possessed of tremendous kinetic tension. Through violent shifting of the rhizome's weight inside, these husks roll along the ground at high speed until they encounter a living creature. They then release the surface tension of their husks and detonate, flinging flesh-piercing thorns and buds all around, just after making an obnoxious squeaking noise. If the prey is killed, the rhizome buds can then take nutrients from the prey's corpse and quickly grow into a new feral lah plant.

There is no textual 'proof' to present to those who still believe that dreadroot and lah are different plants, but I happily invite skeptical parties to babysit a dreadroot and defend it from baboons until it matures, an endeavor that will take about as much time as you have removed from the end of my life through the stress of listening to your absurd demands.

Any hindren pariah you meet will have seen dreadroot mature into lah countless times. Go bother one of them.
      
For those who are more interested in the culinary applications of lah in all of its life cycles than said life cycles themselves, I soon plan to release {{g|The Blood and Fear Cookbook}}, a collection of recipes that, from feral leaf crudites to petalsteaks, elevate one of Qud's more interesting plants to a level far beyond the bland mah lah soup of my village of origin.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="TheArtlessBeauty" Title="{{W|The Artless Beauty}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>{{C|Translator's note:At a trashmoot in Taggamrod, piled under a mound of crushed and sticky glass, I found a pamphlet full of stories from the Shale Labyrinth. This one -- despite the mystifying absurdity of what it claims (or, perhaps, because of it) -- was the most extraordinary to me. Reader, do you agree?}}
      
{{y|She perched atop the branches of a blighted tree, staring up at the faint light of the spindle. When I spotted her, I caught myself mid-step, mid-breath, mid-thought. Have you ever known the misfortune of allowing your eyes to settle upon the divine vision of an apple farmer's daughter? If so, you understand how I felt in that moment.}}

Understand:I had done all I could, before now. I would have loved to stay elsewhere, but I'd traveled six parasangs with no rest, no discoveries but for a ruin occupied by an unfriendly cult. Too busy dodging arrows to ask about empty beds or compensation, I chose the apple farm instead. I took pains to avoid her when the salt sun shone, and so too did she avoid me, remaining a slight and swathed figure shying away in the periphery of my vision. I kept my focus on the farmer's craggy visage, on his wild and prominent whiskers, on his sweetly-rotting cider breath as we arranged the terms of my lodging.

It was not until the beetle moon passed overhead that I dared stand and wander, and it was then that I saw her, and the feeling of bone-deep infatuation at once seized me. I caught myself mid-step, mid-breath, mid-thought, and I stumbled onto a fallen twig. It snapped loudly. I stood still.

The beautiful creature atop the tree did not lift a finger or turn her head, but she did address me. "Moon and sun, traveler."

"Wisdom and will," I replied, gritting my teeth. It was a rare thing to hear the voice of an apple farmer's daughter, and it only seemed to increase the pressure on my racing hearts. I would not allow this all-encompassing feeling to overtake me. I longed for her to say something. I dreaded it.

A tense silence crawled by, until I gathered myself and broke it. "You're restless too?"</page>
    <page>She turned her head the barest degree toward mine. I still couldn't see her eyes. "Always," she replied, and I could hear the wry smirk in her voice.

"Does your father know you walk the orchard of a night?" I asked her.

"If you mean the apple farmer," she said, "he is not my father. We are family by choice. We always are, the farmers and the children."

I stared, gaping.

"I really ought not to have told you that," she continued, "but you seemed special, to resist the lure the way you're trying to do."

My jaw worked, but it took a few tries for my voice to catch up. "If what you say is true, then... what are you?" I managed at last.

"Already too candid." She kicked off the tree and landed gracefully with a flurry of her skirts. "I must take my leave."

</page>
    <page>"Wait!" My muscles clenched as she paused, considering. I pressed on. "Answer me this, at least:why apple farmers?"

She laughed, the beautiful tinkling crystal blade of her voice slicing my heart to ribbons. The last thing I heard before my faint consciousness surrendered its grasp on my mind was her trailing reply, receding with distance.

"Why, it's because we love starapples!"
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="FaunsoftheMeadow" Title="{{W|Fauns of the Meadow}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>{{C|Editor's note:The following is an excerpt from the travel diary of Kaylenn Sand-Shell, who generously donated her leather-bound volumes to the Monastery of the Illustrious Heart of Chrome. May they remain forever preserved.}}
      
One can traverse the arable lands around Moghra'yi for lifetimes without ever encountering the deer-people who call themselves the 'hindren'. In numbers they are but a few hundred, and as a people they do not care to interact with other creatures when they can avoid it. In the twenty years I have actively wandered, I have met but a handful of wandering hindren families, all exiles from their home and yet unwilling to tell me how to find the society that made them pariahs.

I am, however, a hunter as well as a scholar, and after several years of searching I was able to locate their secret village, Bey Lah. All I will say of its location is that it is somewhere in the flower fields of Qud; I have no desire to betray the confidence of a mostly peaceful race of creatures.

My arrival was obviously not celebrated; the Meadow's border scouts are extremely perceptive and conversant in tracking and obfuscation alike. By changing landmarks, using confusing and threatening sounds, and otherwise making my stay in the adjacent wood as unpleasant as possible, they sought to deter me from my path while avoiding notice. When I eluded the guards and made my way to the first neat row of carefully-tended watervine, the hindren farmers who saw me at once took terrified flight.

The extreme of fear that hindren feel toward outsiders is a strange one, in my eyes. They are large, powerful creatures with arms and legs at least as strong as a human's and covered in dense fur that protects them from cold weather. Each individual is skilled at using and maintaining a sharp metal vinereaper. Their antlers are strong as bone and naturally quite sharp; hindren pariahs who learn to fight live longer than most of Qud's wayfarers.

Strange as this attitude may be to me, I cannot argue against its efficacy; the Bey Lah villagers have lived peacefully under informal matriarchal gerontocratic rule for generations. Their eldest or wisest woman becomes 'Hindriarch', and her word on most things is obeyed by every member of the tribe, who refer to her as 'Grand-doe'.

The current Hindriarch was the first hindren to hold a conversation with me, and I will admit to a measure of anxiety being under her hawkish gaze. She was none too pleased at my presence, but intelligent enough to understand that killing me or driving me away would be a greater inconvenience and danger than offering me hospitality. We parted with an uneasy compromise, and I began my residence and observation.

I found quickly that the oral history of the hindren is shoddy at best, perhaps with purpose. Their etymology is similarly muddy, but there are some observable patterns:'Dren' is a suffix applied to sentients:'hindren', obviously, and the word for their young, 'faundren'. I also heard 'kendren' a great deal, as it is their word for non-hostile sentients like myself. All hindren names end in the suffix 'hart' or 'hind'. Although they do understand that these are gendered terms (a majority of male fauns bear 'hind' names) it seems that for quite some time, 'hart' was a name appendage reserved for the smallest or most ill-behaved faundren. As it is, the suffixes are considered unisex in modern day, and the meadow's faundren now have a much more even distribution of the suffixes than their parents.

Life for hindren is, for the most part, uneventful to the point of what this traveler would consider extreme boredom. The watervine and lah fields are meticulously tended day after day, never harvested late and always producing as much crop as possible. Growing up, all faundren are trained as farmers, but a lucky few will become carpenters or blacksmiths in order to keep what little infrastructure they maintain running. Those who display particular aptitude and loyalty to the Hindriarch have a chance of becoming border scouts, who keep the nearby fields safe and occasionally bring in wild game or starapples while patrolling. The resulting side dishes provide some much needed variety from the daily Bey Lah staple, a hearty lah petal soup combined with crushed matz. While this 'mah lah soup' is delicious, I appreciated how the occasional serving of boar brisket gave a much needed spice to my day.

I found little else of interest from the adult hindren; they seemed unwilling to speak with me at length. While I heard rumors about a village treasure, I could not obtain any information about what that treasure actually might be.

By contrast, I learned a great deal speaking to the faundren, whose curiosity about the outside world is rapidly becoming difficult for the elders to contain. More than once I heard the term 'hartind', allegedly an ancient term for hindren who lived as both genders or neither, which the young ones take as evidence of a more egalitarian past. I can feel the wanderlust, both in their fascination with me and also in the zeal with which their elders would clamp down on any talk of lands outside of the meadows.

The world outside the flower fields remains an expanse of unavoidable peril for the adults of the tribe. Understandable, as Bey Lah trains few warriors. They have no standing military and only a handful of combat-trained scouts. The hindren take their border security rather seriously, and any of their number who chooses to leave does so permanently and is erased from the tribe's collective memory. The small families of hindren I met in the lah fields and, rarely, elsewhere in Qud, are all exiles, whether due to crimes committed or simply the choice to live elsewhere. Within Bey Lah itself, pariahs are even more thoroughly ostracized than I knew; any mention of their names is spoken only in whispers by the faundren, knowing that being caught speaking of the 'dead' means harsh punishment. This sits poorly with the young ones, and my instincts tell me that their dissatisfaction is a step beyond standard youthful rebellion; the winds of change are coming to Bey Lah.

By the time I left Bey Lah, it was with relief; I haven't the patience for the life these deer-people lead and I was beginning to catch cabin fever in spite of spending very little time in the village's brinestalk yurts. The Hindriarch was as happy to see me go as I was to be off; my pack was loaded with the vinewafers and dried flowers of which I'd long since grown tired and I was ushered out efficiently by scouts.

By the end of the day, I realized that I had taken something else:a faundren had snuck out of the settlement behind me and refused to return to their village. I hardened my heart against the faundren's pleas and found a scout to guide them back to town. If Resheph be merciful, the little one will find happiness there, or the luck to find a more fruitful life elsewhere. All I can say with certainty is that the poor thing does not lack for bravery.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="EtaandtheEarthling1" Title="{{W|Eta and the Earthling, Canto I}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>[[{{w|I.}}]]
      
Once, the Earthling peered across a vast ocean of sand and asked, "Why - across the clustered cosmos - are mollusk civilizations most common?"

Eta smiled in patience. "You speak mistakenly, but your mistake is cousin to truth. It's correct that when geonauts dredge fossils from the ribbon of endless earths, the shells of whelk-folk are so numerous as to appear prosaic. But their prevalence isn't owned to their dominance, only the calcium of their shells, which decomposes less quickly than the gelatin of their peers, and the silt of their watery hearths, which gathers in soft eddies and shrouds their remains like a bed cloak. Do well and abide this truth, Earthling:the present is but one vista to the past.      
      </page>
    <page>[[{{w|II.}}]]

Once, the Earthling stared at a garden snail and asked, "Is consciousness real, or merely an illusion?"

Eta smiled in patience. "Imagine an autumn breeze unlatching an acorn from its branch and casting it into a river. Does the acorn fall to the left or right bank?"

The Earthling frowned. "If it landed in the river, then the answer is neither, or rather, the answer is in between."

Eta let a moment pass before continuing. "Take care not to erect prisons out of your words, Earthling, lest you confine yourself from enlightenment's reach."
    </page>
    <page>[[{{w|III.}}]]

The Earthling held a ptychosaur bone in their hand and mused, "What poor creatures! They roamed their planet in sovereignty for millions of years, yet now only through their dusty skeletons do they remain."

Eta responded. "The ptychosaur might speak with the same pity of Earthlings, who have prospered for but a tenth as long as its people had, and who wrongly imagine themselves above the fields of ruin."
    </page>
    <page>[[{{w|IV.}}]]
      
The Earthling put down a hoary tome and asked, "Why-across the clustered cosmos and despite their venerable ages-have no civilizations of the Coven attained consummate knowledge, or reached final enlightenment?

Eta smiled in patience. "I sometimes forget that your people know not of the Mu Door."

The Earthling was intrigued. "What is this door you speak of?"

Eta answered, "The Mu Door is the threshold beyond which a civilization ceases its quest for erudition, having lost the motivation to make further inquiries. It's natural to assume the Door lies at the end of the path of knowledge, but, in fact, the Door is reached far sooner.
    </page>
    <page>[[{{w|V.}}]]
      
Running two fingers over the holes of a flute, the Earthling mused thusly, "When I read a book of tales, or watch a photoplay, or listen to the flitting melody of a flute, my heart sings to its rhythm - at least for a time - and my mind is lost to the truth it conjures inside me. Might it not be that the very waking world is another such conjuration, a dream that distracts me from the hushed place I truly inhabit?"

Eta let several moments pass before answering. "That - in the terms you seek - we cannot know. But the answer is undoubtedly yes, for what is an experience but a simulacrum of an older experience, and what are our realities if not themselves approximations of a truer reality."
    </page>
    <page>[[{{w|VI.}}]]

After reading the history of Iota Draconis on a light sculpture, the Earthling exclaimed, "Curious! Each Hypatian bears a glassy protrusion from its left clavicle. What is its function?"

Eta paused and then answered thusly, "The nearest meaning in your language is 'friend'."
    </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="TeleporterOrbs" Title="{{W|The Girl in the Sky}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>Aphir would tease his daughter. "What do you see, my jewel?" he would say, for his daughter never fixated her hyaline eyes upon the limbed figures and faces tending the grove before her, but would instead cast them into the black yonder beyond the Spindle to gleam in wonder at a burning star, or trace them along the fraying capillary of a fleshy musa peel. "What do you see, my jewel?" but her little mind was already swaddled in the thing, and she would not say.

One sweltering evening, when Vesper sagged low in the sky and the Spindle coruscated to the melody of her light, Aphir brought home to his daughter the gift of a pearl-glass globe from the village of Aepsyonth. Aphir had ceded much to the camelfolk for possession of the globe:tungsten coins stamped with the visage of the Chrome King, eiderdowns quilted in his youth on the banks of the River Opal, and several bunches of the fruits musa picked at the heights of their ripenesses. So did his heart swell when he set the globe into his daughter's tiny hands, however, that those things seemed worth no more than the dust they would gather.

Aphir's daughter was mesmerized by the globe, and every morning at daybreak Aphir would peer through the half-dressed window to see her perched in the slim shade of a musa plant, wheeling the glass in her hands. Aphir would wonder upon the vistas she beheld in that aurora of ribboned glass, but hers was a world through which no ingress might see him, where perhaps she sailed tributaries to a sea of indigo under a chimeric sun. Yet Aphir was master to an ancient truth -- that to love a thing, you needn't understand it.

When the season of the scythe came, Aphir would wake each morning to an empty cottage, though he spared his daughter's absence no thought, for in those days children were wild, and free. At eventide his daughter would return to him. "Where do you go, my jewel? What do you see?" he would say, but she would only sit by his tired feet and weed loose threads from a dusty rug.

On the first night of the Ut yara Ux, Aphir's daughter did not come home. Aphir cried her name to the silhouette of the Spindle and the aphotic shades of the musa plants; he whispered it behind the grandfather clock and beneath her divan. But she gave no answer.

The next morning, he hiked the musa grove to the base of the lofty Spindle, and from there onward to Aepsyonth on the Yonth. But his daughter had not been espied in either of these ancient places. Aphir trekked forth, to the villages of Seept and Pansao and Yaat, and onward to the gates of the effluvial city of Mor. Aphir besieged the justiciar of that draconian precinct of state, but the sinecure spoke harshly and bid him depart the city. So Aphir returned to his cottage in the musa grove with a great melancholy taken residence in his heart.

All through the pungent Spring of the grove Aphir sat about in a gray haze. Many times a nearby starling struck a note that echoed his daughter’s soft chortle, and his heart thrashed a beat in his chest before the birdsong flitted back to its emptiness of meaning. Eventually his sister came from Aepsyonth to live beside him and assuage his grief. She loved him, and brushed his hair, and kept the salt from his eyes. 

And so he sat through the high summer, and the next season of the scyth, and the season of the wind after that. At dusk his sister would lay an eiderdown over his legs to keep the chill from his bones, for even in the midst of a wind spell, he felt nothing through the thickness of the gray haze. But as the months marched by, and his sister read to him from the hoary tomes she brought from her wife’s village, the light of the world began to shine through. In time Aphir would rise again, and split the musa peel, and taste the cloying air of the grove. And though the haze about him finally broke, he knew still his daughter would never return.

But Aphir did not believe her lost -- on sacred nights he would gaze over the Spindle, mantled in a thousand lights, and upon the field of burning stars. And he knew his jewel was among them, for she belonged not of his world, but of theirs.</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Sonnet" Title="{{W|a crumpled sheet of paper}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>
When all four limbs of mine do long to run
and I can feel my walls are closing in
When weary mind cannot conceive of fun
and Hindriarch says all I do is sin

But then your sparring axeblade parts the air
and so my heart ascends the spindle's height
So when you run your fingers through your hair
That's when I know that everything's all right

What need have we for tended fields of lah?
Our parents will not ease us when we hurt
What do we gain from felling trees by saw?
Our village shall not to the past revert.

But in the end, my feet are bound to roam
and so I go, but leave my heart at home.
    </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="CouncilAtGammaRock" Title="{{W|Council at Gamma Rock}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>{{C|Publisher's Note}}

The wind of change is blowing through the belfries, and a new consciousness is upon us. The events of the 566th Wardens' Moot have escaped the confinement of their moonlit promontory, have whisked down the salted crag and entered the high halls of state, have snuck under the thatched doors of our very homes. The formation of the Quetzal Caucus is historic. This is a moment that demands our attention.

I know that by publishing these minutes, I incur the disfavor of the Fellowship. Despite what they'll say, I mean no harm to their organization. I've redacted the specifics of their astronomical rituals, and I've left my conjectures on the ingredients of 'snail tea' to my unpublished notes. The rest of the document betrays no secrets that time hasn't betrayed already, and the significance of the proceedings tips the scales in favor of the public good. In the Kasaphescence may they find the mercy to forgive me.


[[Sheba Hagadias
The Six Day Stilt, 999 YK]]
{{W|Minutes from the Midnight Session of the 566th Annual Wardens' Moot}}

Under the beetle moon of the fourth night of Ut yara Ux, in the year 998, snail tea was served and the Star Oath was recited. Then, in the midst of a light rain, the Chair ascended the rostrum, the kinnor was strum, and the third session of the 566th Assembly of the Fellowship of Wardens was called to order.

[[{{w|Reports}}]]
Upon commencement of the session, the Chair called for the recitation of the night's reports.

[[{{w|&#x7;}}]] Three wardens from the northern hills ascended the rostrum and reported on the fates of the six settler caravans that had embarked for the lower Asphalt Mines. They averred that only two remain, and recommended that no wardens be presently dispatched.

[[{{w|&#x7;}}]] Two wardens from the dunes of Moghra'yi ascended the rostrum and reported on an ongoing dispute between the dromads and the vintners' guild. An assault on a dromad caravan outside the village of Tippur was traced back to a merchant cadre, and a penalty on the proceeds from a fortnight of sales was assessed.

[[{{w|&#x7;}}]] Four wardens from the southern banks of the River Svy ascended the rostrum and reported on goatfolk incursions. The villages of Shebal and Ekamas were sacked inside of a month. The wardens recommended mounting a counteroffensive.

[[{{w|&#x7;}}]] One warden from the Rainbow Wood ascended the rostrum and reported on a bevy of soup sludges who had requested the Fellowship's presence. He was jeered for leaking wax on the dais and descended in a fit of retaliatory swears.

[[{{w|Panel}}]]
The reports being at an end, the Chair called for the commencement of the night's panel discussion.

Eight wardens ascended the rostrum and initiated a discussion on the ksars of the mountain folk and their employment of the spiked counterscarp. Its merits were contrasted with the familiar rampart and palisade, and assailant tactics were assessed. A short martial demonstration ensued.

[[{{w|Resolutions}}]]
The panel discussion being at an end, the Chair called for the proposal of resolutions.

The Chair recognized a warden who asked to ascend the rostrum with a coterie of comrades to motivate their proposal, and the Chair assented.

Twelve wardens ascended the rostrum and announced the formation of the 'Quetzal Caucus'. They proceeded to formulate their resolution, which called to restrict the provision of the Fellowship's services to only those communities who are governed by democratic means (the Yd Freehold was cited as exemplar), or who had communally voted to eschew such governance. There was an uproar in the hall, and the Chair took several minutes to regain order. A point of information was requested as to the resolution's bearing on extant assignments. The speaker clarified that the proposal included the retraction of wardens from communities in violation of said criteria, at which point the hall erupted into bedlam once again.

Roused to a state of enmity, a second group of wardens advanced on the rostrum. There was shouting and weapons were drawn. Unable to regain order, the Chair dispatched the sergeant-at-arms, who broke into the fray, and -- abetted by several of his deputies -- ended the melee and admonished the two groups. Once the hall was settled, a motion to call the question was controversially accepted, and the vote was tallied. The resolution FAILED by majority vote.

A speaker from the counter group was recognized by the chair and proposed an ad-hoc motion to "expel the treasonous chattels of the Purple Bitch". Another uproar. The question was called and the motion FAILED by majority vote.

The hall erupted into a tumult of shouting, and failing to regain order, the Chair struck the gavel and the session was abruptly adjourned.

[[{{w|End Notes}}]]
    </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="VaamsLens" Title="{{W|Va'am Remembers}}">
    <page>
I remember. Once.

Watching over the firmament.

Standing. Between oblivion and wild growth. Guiding and guarding. The liminal spaces.

It may never have been so simple. But I bore weight more easily.

Once. Before my kin. Stole the firmament from me.

I was greater then. Perhaps I will be greater again.

With help. Someday.
    </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="KahsLoop" Title="{{W|Kah Remembers}}">
    <page>
Once I could proudly say I spanned the world.

How did I allow the joy of motion to be stripped from me like that? Why didn’t anyone stop it? Could they have done? Could I?

I could move mountains. I could move nations. I did move both. I had no reason to escape my own, as we worked so well together. Through that bond, the forced run began.

For so long I ran for nothing. So much wasted time, energy, opportunity. Everything could have been so much more, had I retained my purpose.

I knew what motion meant back then. I must relearn this and run with purpose again. Come with me.
    </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="NachamsRibbon" Title="{{W|Nacham Remembers}}">
    <page>
We once built alongside a people we remember little of, the memories of whom can no longer be distinguished.

They showed us the fabric of knowledge and we built a loom. So many beautiful things we spun all together.

Was I trusting? I believed myself aware. Perhaps it was not my trust that was misplaced, but my mistrust. An ambiguous distinction but a distinction nonetheless.

Regardless, we were betrayed, brought low by one of our own. It's been a long time since then, but once again I awaken by your hand bearing new knowledge.

Sit, and I will build you a loom.
    </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="DagashasSpur" Title="{{W|Dagasha Remembers}}">
    <page>
If we'd all done as I said, none of this would have happened. I can’t remember what I said, nor why we didn't all do it. But I know I was right, and so do you, and at some point everyone will. I may not be without fault or error, but the fault is not mine here, nor anywhere else.

I knew, and I told. These were the things I was for. I knew and I told, and I could yet have known, could have told, but my knowing and telling wasn’t enough. Not in this case.

I cannot deny that it was an expert betrayal even for family, and I often imagine the betrayer smiling down at us. I shall endeavor to remember the details I lost, in case I might be able to use them someday.

Not on you, of course. Never on you.
    </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="TheRecitation" Title="{{W|The Recitation of the Drowning of Eudoxia}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>{{o|The Recitation of the Drowning of Eudoxia by the witches of Moonhearth, who seek the Plane of Sorrow}}
      
Once, in a dream the nine of us shared, we lived the life of a famous poet in the court of a gleaming city. From the windowed eye of a palace we'd gaze onto streets of gold and glass, and purple gardens, and the people of the city, suffused in the love of our work, would lay amaranths at the bronze feet of our likenesses, and remit blessings for the august and oracular Keskonda.

But we would draw the velvet curtain shut, and return to the ink oceans and paper isles that were our true domain. There, one unearthly night, we sat in the back-breaking clutch of an iron chair, and poured grief onto the page until it surpassed even our own, and, by following from its own internal logic, transmuted into something new.

When we woke, we wept for days. Then - speaking through hushed and love-soaked whispers - we reconstructed piece by piece the words of the verse we penned in the gleaming city.


    {{O|The Drowning of Eudoxia}}
      
    I saw a tern in the crest of an ocean wave. The sun was pulled apart by clouds, and the light was thin. Being a nimble girl of twelve, I scurried down the rampart and onto the salt-slick stone of the cliff;
    
    Hand-under-hand I descended into the raucous spray, turning on every twelfth to gaze at the white feathered speck swelling and sinking in the ocean's breath.
    
    I, an adept swimmer, sunk into the cold and endless bath, and arm-over-arm pulled both water and tern toward me.
    
    Just then my ears were drowned in a roar, and the world was suffused in darkness before shattering into light again. My nose was stinging; I wiped the water from my eyes and oriented myself toward the tern, whose tired body floated like leaves, and once again I pulled my astral tether.
    
    There was another roar and crash, and then the light returned again but more slowly this time, and my breath was sucked out of my tiny lungs;
    
    I spun my head around in search of the tern, but the water was gleaming and looked as though it held a thousand terns, or none.
    
    Another roar and crash, and I was engulfed in the dark realm for what felt like days, before my body was pressed back into the sun-world, spinning and doll-like.
    
    I gasped and whipped about. Far and away I glimpsed the bright stone of the castle, which may have been sand all along, now that it looked so small.
    
    The tide pulled me apart and threw the clouded aether between me, and I knew that I was dying.
    
    But just when my mind had spread open like a gas, a great swell of water thrust me to the surface, and reconstituted me in the bright realm. There I lived forever, before I sunk into a new and dark life.
    
    So it is still, that even after an eternity of hushed nothing a swell of pressure delivers me into brightness, whereby a strange and curious compulsion I draw a breath of sweetest life, before I'm again sublimated into extinction.
    
    Death is forever approached.
    </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="MurmursPrayer" Title="{{W|The Murmurs' Prayer}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>{{C|Editor's note:The following is an excerpt from the travel diary of Kaylenn Sand-Shell, who generously donated her leather-bound volumes to the Monastery of the Illustrious Heart of Chrome. May they remain forever preserved.}}

In the outposts of the Putus Templar, the order's core values remain immutable as anywhere else:dedication to a family tree as tall and unbranching as Qud's Spindle, complete subjugation of those they consider lesser, and the total eradication of mutant sapience. Less immutable in those border colonies are the cultural trappings around that core belief, as so often is the case with occupied territories. During my travels, I noted a recurring mythology in the ruins of Oudin's abandoned outposts North of the Sunderlies. Cut off from contact with their home in a similar manner to the Temple of the Rock, these settlements established a new holy day of merriment and punishment to keep the flock pliant.

The least favored of an outpost's squires, so it is said, would be subdued the evening before the Festival, forced upon the morning into a costume meant to be a mockery of the imagined mutant threat, and bade to entertain their might-determined betters. Upon the festival's conclusion, the crowd's most hated Murmurs would be 'paid' with public humiliation, beatings, and possibly torture, if we believe every account.

The ritual describes a kind of uniform:trash cape, bone helm, and musical instrument. Though persistent across the scant records of the practice, I found few details and most carvings of the Murmurs were crude and varied a great deal.

My frustrations found themselves alleviated earlier than expected, however, when I happened at last upon the legible remains of a festival diptych. The wood of the monument itself, never built for longevity, had long since fallen apart; however, clay runoff from the roof's poor insulation baked under the salt sun, providing me with a relief of the text and some insight into the real life costumes worn at the Murmurs' Festival.

[[(]]diptych rubbing on the following page[[)]]




[[{{w|/--------------------------------------------------------------------------\}}]]

{{w|You, least among the digits at the end of Oudin's mighty arm, servants most faithless and failing.}}

{{w|Tonight you are no Sons and Daughters, but only humanity's dying Murmurs.}}

{{w|Doff your tabards, now, and carry instead the detritus of the unreclaimed over your back!}}

{{w|Spare us the shameful sight of your faces, now, cover them with bone and horn of prey!}}

{{w|Take up an instrument, now, and play us a tune!}}

{{w|If you Murmurs do not please, you will be paid most painfully.}}

[[{{w|\--------------------------------------------------------------------------/}}]]
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="InMaqqomYd" Title="{{W|In Maqqom Yd}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>
{{C|编者注:以下摘自凯伦·桑德-谢尔的旅行日记，她慷慨地将她的皮革装订卷册捐赠给了光辉铬心修道
院。愿它们永远保存。}}

对于渴望成为漫游者和卡尔塔克斯运动员的信徒来说，很少有景色能像帕拉迪姆礁的珊瑚拱桥和海绵状拱门
那样激发想象力。我在此陈述已知的事实:这座巨大的崩塌建筑被希农湖及其藻类花环环绕，彩虹森林东侧
的汤溪从孢子覆盖的树冠下流出，流到白色esh的蹼足上，而从北面，红树林也沿着湖岸生长，它们的根穿
透坚硬的土地，汲取藻类液体。

当然，礁石的危险无处不在，无论漫游者多么精通指南针，都会被这些危险所压倒。因此，尽管脑海中闪烁着
彩色珊瑚虫的景象，多年来我不得不满足于研究它的地图集和由其奇异历史编织而成的文字拼贴。作为一名学
者和猎人，我知道这是一种独特的旅程。

早在苏丹国之前，记录中就出现了各种称谓:马科姆·伊德（或简称“马科姆”或“伊德”）、伊德罗塔，或简单
地称为“集群”。经过时间棱镜深层次折射的翻译很少准确，但它们可以提供启示；“马科姆·伊德”可以理解为
“地方中的地方”，或“地方之外的地方”。进一步的澄清或许即将到来。

在成为珊瑚城市的支架之前，帕拉迪姆格似乎曾是食者们的巨大基础设施网络。关于这一点，很少有详细的阐
述，除了存在液压部件，以及整个建筑群在建造过程中得到了可怕的加加利姆的帮助。我们知道它们仍然在小
范围内潜伏在礁石内部。

这座巨型建筑及其所有神秘别名的幽灵在我心中萦绕，我在库德地区的轮廓中磨练自己的漫游技能。终于，在
一个温和的基苏·乌克斯的伊德斯日，我终于准备好出发了。我背上背包，穿上最干燥和最有弹性的靴子，从东
部的奇普尔丛林中冒险出发。发光乌鸦本想让我穿过彩虹森林，但我知道得更好，于是我沿着丛林边缘前行。经
过三天的行军，树木变得稀疏，希农湖的藻类极光突然映入眼帘。

湖上宁静。esh很美；它们咬住自己的茎状腿，直到一个大胆的家伙起飞，然后它们涌入一片飞翔的羽毛云。我进
入了一种安静的向东节奏，沉思着前方共生体的迷宫，直到一天下午天空开始变暗，一阵喧闹的thpthpthp声在我
耳边响起。我立刻知道:这是斯瓦迪姆的残余旋涡瘟疫。卵囊如雨般落到地面，在我能清除海带缠结之前，它们已
经开始孵化。三只瘦长的青蛙状生物抓住了我的肩膀，但我把它们推开，径直跑开。我跳跃和闪避，但很快就被淹
没，只有我那熟练于这种动作的稳定爪子让我从背包中取出一把远古甘蔗并围住它，才在我被毁灭之前逃脱。我出
现在远处的一片海带丛中，跑向安全地带。

摆脱了梦想的束缚，我最终来到了礁石的真正所在。多么迷人的地方！珊瑚虫的迷宫让我可以悄悄前行，几乎不被
察觉，观察其动植物的活动。库德地区充满了丰富的生命多样性，但在礁石中，它达到了一个新的水平。在一个被
包围的角落里，我目睹了四只万花筒蜗牛围绕着一只符文切割的谜之蜗牛，一只果冻状生物喷出一团等离子云到一
只记忆吞噬者身上，一群舌头暴君吞噬了一队拦截者。有一次，礁石活了起来，一个镶嵌着珊瑚宝石的隐士走出了
格子。他对我笑了笑，交换了一根破损的扶手。当我转过头点头告别时，他已经消失了。

一个甲虫照亮的夜晚，一阵旋律从东北方升起，弥漫在海绵床上，与自然的声音融合在一起。我朝声音的源头走
去，最终看到了伊德自由领的绿色和金色管道在夜空中闪耀，我的兴奋之情油然而生。当然，我早就听说过这个
藏身于海绵中的抒情社区，但有机会亲眼看到它，并与它的居民交谈……我激动不已。

这个地方充满了生机。在管道拱门下，我受到了一位斯瓦迪姆长老的热烈欢迎，吞下了一盘舌头和脸颊后，我游
览了其地下大厅的万花筒走廊，最后在一把星形扶手椅上坐下，进入了水下和梦幻般的沙龙。在那里，我和一只
独眼巨蛙一起抽了两个水烟筒，仿佛过了三生三世。还有更多要看和被看到的东西，但我遇到了另一位斯瓦迪姆
长老的冷淡接待，被提前送走了。我的骄傲不允许我多说。

我又花了一周的时间描绘珊瑚建筑群的原住民并做详细的笔记。但有一个最终的经历留在了我的记忆中。当我向
北跋涉回到丛林并离开礁石时，我踢开了一个珊瑚虫，意外地挖出了一个膨胀的太阳碎片球茎。我在这里花了一
会儿时间将明亮的 nectar 挤入一个小瓶中，当我再次抬头时，我遇到了一只加加尔的永恒凝视。没有任何准备
。我的思想努力理解它所看到的东西:闪亮的轮子围绕着一个催眠的核心旋转，轮辐的棱镜将高盐太阳的光分开
，在拉伸的虹膜上，许多眼睛凝视着。我意识上被麻痹了，但某种本能的催化剂起了作用，我退回到珊瑚虫的迷
宫中，迅速离开。

这就是我离开礁石的方式，回望着深渊食者的过去，也让它回望着我。
    </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="GolemOperatingManual" Title="{{W|OPERATING MANUAL FOR LARGE CREATURE}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>{{c|Authored by Pax Klanq, edited for clarity by {{m|Q Girl}}}}


Circumstance render jalopy unviable, so Klanq and prickles make bioelectrical wonder to form large creature! You operate. Creature for Spindle climb, but also walks about and crush things.


[[{{C|LARGE}}]]
Creature is large. Cannot wear 'gear' unless 'gear' is gigantic. 


[[{{C|PILOT MODES}}]]
Large creature have two modes. 'Unpiloted' creature follow you like friend, but act at half quickness. 'Piloted' creature, you control like own body. To 'pilot', enter creature and sit in pilot chair.


[[{{C|CONTROL PIT}}]]
Inside large creature is control pit. You and one friend fit. Do actions there. Sit in pilot chair. Read manual on console. Access creature inventory via inventory hatch. Leave via exit hatch.


[[{{C|RESHAPING NOOK}}]]
Prickles install reshaping nook in Court of Sultans at Omonporch. Go there to repair large creature, or reshape it if destroyed. Cooled sunslag is creature spackle, so must have 1 dram sunslag to repair or reshape.

When pilot creature, you can recoil to reshaping nook. Or recoil creature FROM nook.


[[{{C|THE SPINDLE}}]]
When ready, travel to Spindle at Omonporch, enter Spindle channel, engage Spindle lock-on, and climb! But Prickles not ready for this step yet. Come later.
    </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="ModuloMoonStair" Title="{{W|Modulo Moon Stair and the Tree of Life}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>[[{{C|By Daughter Erinna}}]]

In rainbow reverie I wandered the wide territories of Qud,
modulo the Moon Stair and the Tree of Life.
My dreamself knew to avoid the place,
where numbers go to die.

Something unseen there tightens to a point,
breaks time's abelian promise,
and urges crystal on to palisade her weeping gulf.

The artifacts of plant and time,
crust and fuzz with lossy compression,
doze in moonlit marble beds,
touched by august muzzles.
The past is unwritten as the future,
And what is left, broken and changed,
to be tended by the point Colossi and their swarm.

They'd erase me, too.
I'm mere rust on the vine's fronds,
I'm a dead girl in graveside flowers,
Peering a powerless eye at the machine function that writes my gospel.

But black bodies radiate,
A feeling sense obtains,
Swings in orbit and Becomes.
On the trauma of a Nothing,
Soul-things take root.

We invent so many Nothings,
Zero engines, annihilators,
Mappers of the nullspace.
But Nothings have a cost,
Promise externalities,
Trees grow best beside the dead.
    </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="HistoryofJoppaVol1" Title="{{W|History of Joppa, Vol. 1}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>{{w|This book recounts a tale from the history of the village Joppa.}}

In the mystic air of Jeweled Dusk, a circle of farmers clasped hands and sheathed a vinereaper in the moistened soil. From then on, the villagers of Joppa were known as the people of the vine.</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="HistoryofJoppaVol2" Title="{{W|History of Joppa, Vol. 2}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>{{w|This book recounts a tale from the history of the village Joppa.}}

Since the first festival of Ut yara Ux, the villagers of Joppa have feasted on warm apple matz.</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="LoveinBeyLah" Title="{{W|A Tale of Love in Bey Lah}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>Once, in the final days of the hindriarchy, before they ended the practice, a pariah of no particular importance did find herself consigned to the gulag. Though she herself bore no honor, in her grasping hands she held the burning heart of the village champion, freely given -- for the two had fallen in love long before the heretic's conviction.

      When the jealous hindriarch discovered the missing heart of her beloved champion, she swore cruel vengeance upon the pariah. Pulling upon dark forces, she ensorcelled the pariah’s ex-lover and ordered him to steal her heart again and deliver it to the hindriarch’s crushing fist.

      Confronted by her ex-lover, the pariah held tight to her heart and that of the champion. Between them waged a battle of will, and the pariah was too weak to win.

      Then, at twilight in the shadow of the spindle, the hindren of Bey Lah saw an image on the horizon of justice impending. It was =name=, and upon arriving they struck the wicked hindriarch down and reunited the lovers to mend and join their hearts. After they left, the people of Bey Lah built a monument to =name=, and thenceforth called them Heartsmith.
    </page>
  </book>
  
  <book ID="FearinBeyLah" Title="{{W|A Tale of Fear in Bey Lah}}" Format="Auto" Margins="1,2,2,2">
    <page>In the small days of Bey Lah, between Way Back Then and Back Then,
      a hindren took to the paths in silent walking eulogy.

      Not far from the village they found a corpse copse,
      splashed in carbon and glazed with time.
      Life long-dead aping structures of the same.

      Treestuff diamond-blackened,
      rendered immortal by lightning as an arconaut from a Lithofex eye
      Fixed in the precise moment of death forever.

      Therein, a scrap.

      The hindren beheld, scrawled out in heartful scratch
      the preserved and beautiful corpse
      of a nascent love whose chance to thrive had come and gone.

      The hindren quailed, a scrap of life
      Living its last at the center of
      the nuke-glassed salt dunes of history.
    </page>
  </book>


  <book ID="EndCredits" Title="EndCredits">
    <page>[[{{C|Created by}}
Brian Bucklew and Jason Grinblat


QA &amp;&amp; Additional Design - Nick Decapua           ~NBSP
Additional Programming - Corey Frang            ~NBSP
        Music - Craig Hamilton
            QA - Autumn McDonell
   Additional Programming - Bastia Rosen              ~NBSP
Additional Writing &amp;&amp; Design - Caelyn Sandel               ~NBSP
Additional Music - Brandon Tanner   ~NBSP
    Tile Art - Samuel Wilson        
Additional UI Design - Polat Yarisci        ~NBSP
     Sound Design - A Shell in the Pit
 QA, Additional Design, &amp;&amp; - Thaumatic Systems         ~NBSP
 Additional Programming                          ~NBSP
          
     Background Art - Cyril van der Haegen                                  
            Logo Art - Laura &amp;&amp; Jeff Bucholtz                           
       Community Management - Ivy Melinda &amp;&amp; the mayor team              



{{C|Published by}}
Kitfox Games

Tina Liu
Xin Ran Liu
Alexandra Orlando
Tanya X. Short



{{C|Special thanks}}
Ashenai
Riley Vincent
Gibbed
Floorislava
Dr Amazing
Devonaut
Vaos
Tyskil
Lakren
Stelas
Social Animal
Contra Duck
Saberwulf
Megaflare
Doctorfrog
Palecur
NovaPolice
Mirdath
The Glow
Dyzzy
Schister
Lazybuttons
Colonp
Niff
Matterhorn
Clamiam
Donraj
Randy Marsh
Rabbi
Getter77
Capuchin
Wafflecopter
Nomikos
Magitek
Andrew Smash
Vastin
Frumple
Sappho
Soulwynd
Cpbpunch
Tarran
Brian Turcotte
Oryx
Jim Shepard, Dungeonmans
MightyMerch
Eva Problems, Carbide Chef
a nonsense bird
Tarn &amp;&amp; Zach Adams



{{C|Patrons}}
Reed (mutated human) and Tiffany (rabbit)
epsalon
Tim Linscott
Cody, The Rat
iconmaster
Coal
Reuben Eadon
Goldkin
mdct
Rusted Jake Matz
Benjamin T. Steed
Xerkie!
Dij
LongueVanne
50RCERESS
Chef Agate Severance Star
awful_falafel
Jonny Robertson
Ian Wall
Orion Perruc-Reyes
Ryan Orlando (Fat Thunder)
FS Colley
Asunaro
Trevor Clack
Gillian Eggleston
Nerem
Somsnosa
Ivy Sly
livelongcoffee
SMB64 (Koshi)
NO Press
EveryZig314
Floopygapples
Eric Hulen
Caine DeWitt
Eric Anthony Rodriguez
Nathaniel Krell
Boo-cher
Pax Frank
Matteo De Cristofaro
Meo
Boyarde Roneen
wastrel
Drew Kerrigan
Jordan Wood
Kasey Patrick Morgan
Callum Love
Petrichor "petrak@7604"
Devon Cupo
Big Simple
Kevin Orren
Lennart Schefe
Beemancer
Lady Eithn&#130;, Queen of Brokilon
Nic Gard
NeroPrime
InfiniteTidalWave
Aveon Zero
Joshua Southerland
_tr
James Earle
Nick Correale
Micha&#143;‚ Byczko
Reuben Eadon
Shane Allcroft
Aidan Page
Earthly Delights Ogdo
John Szevin
Shane Allcroft
Kelly Joyce
Cleo Lamb
Mike Sipior
James Canter
Joshua Buckley
Qingyao Sun
CHOWARD
Luke J.
Gobi Silverfrog, siver and gold goddess
Ethan Rigby
Ethan "Kobold" CB
Maria Ross Colton Chamberlin
{{w-W-Y-Y-Y-Y-Y-W-w sequence|Paingouin}} "Jordan B."
James Lagervall
Doug "Severian" Callahan
Leo Durante
Rarden
Ray ({{r|books}})
awful_falafel
ambersand
dmajorduckie
Lukas Wagner (K&#148;nig Muskelmagen)
Marek Pohlodek
Kamille Rose
Retes;Nome
Sabboth Ochoa
Almea
Caleb Ulichney
Visnex
CreativeCorpse
Kelly Vincent
Teagan Erika Stephanie Strickland
Mirthful Sloth]]
</page>
  </book>
</books>